<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- 
     draft-rfcxml-general-template-standard-01
  
     This template includes examples of the most commonly used features of RFCXML with comments 
     explaining how to customise them. This template can be quickly turned into an I-D by editing 
     the examples provided. Look for [REPLACE], [REPLACE/DELETE], [CHECK] and edit accordingly.
     Note - 'DELETE' means delete the element or attribute, not just the contents.
     
     Documentation is at https://authors.ietf.org/en/templates-and-schemas
-->
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
      category="std" 
      docName="draft-ietf-netconf-privcand-09" 
      ipr="trust200902" 
      obsoletes="" 
      updates="6241,8526,9144" 
      submissionType="IETF" 
      xml:lang="en" 
      version="3"
      consensus="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="NETCONF/RESTCONF Private Candidates">NETCONF and RESTCONF Private Candidate Datastores</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-netconf-privcand-09"/>
    <author fullname="James Cumming" initials="JG" surname="Cumming">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <email>james.cumming@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Robert Wills" initials="R" surname="Wills">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rowills@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026"/>
    <!-- On draft subbmission:
         * If only the current year is specified, the current day and month will be used.
         * If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, the current day will
           be used
         * If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month and day="1" will be used.
    -->
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- "Internet Engineering Task Force" is fine for individual submissions.  If this element is 
          not present, the default is "Network Working Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as 
          a nod to the history of the RFC Series. -->
    <keyword>NETCONF</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a mechanism to extend the Network Configuration Protocol 
	     (NETCONF) and RESTCONF protocol to support multiple clients making configuration changes simultaneously and
         ensuring that they commit only those changes that they defined.</t>
      <t>This document addresses two specific aspects: The interaction with a private candidate
        over the NETCONF and RESTCONF protocols and the methods to identify and resolve conflicts between
        clients.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC6241">NETCONF</xref> and <xref target="RFC8040">RESTCONF</xref>
	       both provide a mechanism for one or more
         clients to make configuration changes to a device running as a NETCONF/RESTCONF
         server.  Each client has the ability to make one or more
         configuration changes to the server's shared candidate configuration.<br/><br/>
		 
		 As the name shared candidate suggests, all clients have access to the same candidate
		 configuration.  This means that multiple clients may make changes to the shared
		 candidate prior to the configuration being committed.  This behaviour may be
		 undesirable as one client may unwittingly commit the configuration changes made
		 by another client.  <br/><br/>
		 
		 NETCONF provides a way to mitigate this behaviour by allowing clients
		 to place a lock on the shared candidate.  The placing of this lock means that
		 no other client may make any changes until that lock is released.  This behaviour
		 is, in many situations, also undesirable.  <br/><br/>

		 Many network devices support candidate configurations within the CLI interface, 
     where a user (machine or otherwise) is able to edit a self-contained copy of a device's 
     configuration without blocking other users from doing so.<br/><br/>
	 
	     This document specifies the extensions to the NETCONF protocol in order to support
	     the use of private candidates.  It also describes how the RESTCONF protocol can be
	     used on a system that implements private candidates.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Updates to RFC 6241 and RFC 8526</name>
        <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC6241"/> to describe how 
          the &lt;edit-config&gt;, &lt;copy-config&gt;, &lt;get&gt;, 
          &lt;get-config&gt;, &lt;commit&gt;, &lt;cancel-commit&gt;, 
          &lt;delete-config&gt;, &lt;discard-changes&gt;, &lt;lock&gt; 
          and &lt;unlock&gt; operations work with a private 
          candidate datastore.  These updates are described in
          <xref target="section_updated_netconf_operations"/>.  This
	        document also adds a new &lt;update&gt; operation, described in
	        <xref target="section_new_netconf_operations"/>.</t>
        <t>This document also updates <xref target="RFC8526"/> to describe 
          how the &lt;edit-data&gt; and &lt;get-data&gt; operations work 
          with a private candidate datastore.  These updates are described in
          <xref target="section_updated_netconf_operations"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Updates to RFC 9144</name>
        <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC9144"/> to augment the
          &lt;compare&gt; operation to describe how it works with the
          private candidate datastore.  These updates are described in
          <xref target="section_updates_to_compare"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Limitations using the shared candidate configuration for multiple clients</name>
        <t>The following sections describe some limitations and mitigation factors in
        more detail for the use of the shared candidate configuration during multi-client
        configuration over NETCONF or RESTCONF.</t>
        <section>
          <name>Issues</name>
          <section>
            <name>Unintended deployment of alternate users configuration changes</name>
            <t>Consider the following scenario:</t>
            <ol>
              <li>Client 1 modifies item A in the shared candidate configuration</li>
              <li>Client 2 then modifies item B in the shared candidate configuration</li>
              <li>Client 2 then issues a &lt;commit&gt; RPC</li>
            </ol>
            <t>In this situation, both client 1 and client 2 configurations will be committed by
              client 2.  In a machine-to-machine environment client 2 may not have been aware of
              the change to item A and, if they had been aware, may have decided not to proceed.
            </t>
          </section>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Mitigation strategies when using a shared candidate datastore</name>
            <section>
              <name>Locking the shared candidate configuration datastore</name>
              <t>
                In order to resolve unintended deployment of alternate users configuration changes
                as described above NETCONF provides the ability to lock a datastore in order to
                restrict other users from editing and committed changes.
              </t>
              <t>This does resolve the specific issue above, however, it introduces another issue.
                Whilst one of the clients holds a lock, no other client may edit the configuration.
                This will result in the client failing and having to retry.  Whilst this may be a
                desirable consequence when two clients are editing the same section of the configuration,
                where they are editing different sections this behaviour may hold up valid operational
                activity.</t>
              <t>Additionally, a lock placed on the shared candidate configuration datastore must also lock the
              running configuration, otherwise changes committed directly into the running datastore
              may conflict.</t>
        <t>Finally, this locking mechanism isn't available to RESTCONF clients.</t>
            </section>
            <section>
              <name>Always use the running configuration datastore</name>
              <t>The use of the running configuration datastore as the target for all configuration
              changes does not resolve any issues regarding blocking of system access in the case a
              lock is taken, nor does it provide a solution for multiple NETCONF and RESTCONF clients as each
              configuration change is applied immediately and the client has no knowledge of the
              current configuration at the point in time that they commenced the editing activity nor
              at the point they commit the activity.</t>
            </section>
            <section>
              <name>Fine-grained (partial) locking</name>
              <t><xref target="RFC5717"/> describes a partial lock mechanism that
                can be used on specific portions of the shared candidate datastore.</t>
              <t>Partial locking does not solve the issues of staging a set of
                configuration changes such that only those changes get committed in a
                commit operation, nor does it solve the issue of multiple clients
                editing the same parts of the configuration at the same time.</t>
              <t>Partial locking additionally requires that the client is aware of
              any interdependencies within the servers YANG models in order to lock all
              parts of the tree.</t>
              <t>Finally, partial locking is not widely implemented.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
  
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Definitions and terminology</name>
      <section>
        <name>Session specific datastore</name>
        <t>A session specific datastore is a configuration datastore that
          is bound to the specific NETCONF session or RESTCONF request,
          unlike the shared candidate and running configuration datastores which
          have only one per system.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="definition_shared_candidate">
        <name>Shared candidate configuration</name>
        <t>The candidate configuration datastore defined in
          <xref target="RFC6241"/> is referenced as the shared candidate
          configuration in this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="definition_private_candidate">
        <name>Private candidate configuration</name>
        <t>A private candidate configuration is a session specific candidate
          configuration datastore.</t>
        <t>When a private candidate is used by NETCONF, the specific session
	  (and user) that created the private
          candidate configuration is the only session (user) that has access
          to it over NETCONF.  Devices may expose this to other users through
          other interfaces but this is out of scope for this document.</t>
	    <t>When a private candidate is used by RESTCONF, the client that created
          the private candidate configuration is the only client that has access
          to it over RESTCONF.</t>
        <t>The private candidate configuration contains a full copy of the running
          configuration when it is created (in the same way as a branch does in
          a source control management system and in the same way as the candidate
          configuration datastore as defined in <xref target="RFC6241"/>).
          When the private candidate datastore is in use, any operations that target
          the &lt;candidate&gt; configuration datastore (for example, &lt;edit-config&gt; and &lt;edit-data&gt; operations)
          actually make changes to the private candidate datastore instead of the shared candidate configuration datastore.</t>
        <t>Obtaining this private candidate over NETCONF or RESTCONF will display the entire
          configuration, including all changes made to it.  Performing a &lt;commit&gt; 
          operation will merge the changes from the private candidate into the running 
          configuration (the same as a merge in source code management systems).  This
          merge is performed in two steps and is described further in
          <xref target="section_updates_to_commit"/>.
          A &lt;discard-changes&gt; operation will revert the private candidate to 
          the branch's initial state or it's state at the last &lt;update&gt; 
          (whichever is most recent).</t>
        <t>All changes made to this private candidate configuration are held
           separately from any other candidate configuration changes, whether
           made by other users to the shared candidate or any other private candidate,
           and are not visible to or accessible by any other configuration session.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Private candidates solution</name>
      <t>The use of private candidates resolves the issues
        detailed earlier in this document.</t>
      <t>NETCONF sessions and RESTCONF clients are able to utilize private candidates
         to streamline network operations, particularly for
         machine-to-machine communication.</t>
      <t>Using this approach, clients may improve their performance and reduce the
        likelihood of blocking other clients from continuing with valid operational
        activities.</t>
      <t>One or more private candidates may exist at any one time, however, a
        private candidate SHOULD:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>Be accessible by one client only</li>
        <li>Be visible by one client only</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Additionally, the choice of using a shared candidate configuration
         datastore or a private candidate configuration datastore MUST be for
         the entire duration of the NETCONF session.</t>
      <section>
        <name>What is a private candidate</name>
        <t>A private candidate is defined in the <xref target="definition_private_candidate">definitions and terminology</xref>
          section of this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="section_when_created">
        <name>When is a private candidate created</name>
        <t>A private candidate datastore is created when the first RPC that requires access
        to it is sent to the server.  This could be, for example, an &lt;edit-config&gt;.</t>
        <t>When the private candidate is created a copy of the running configuration is
        made and stored in it.  This can be considered the same as creating a branch in a
        source code repository.</t>
        <artwork>
          +----------------------------&gt; private candidate
         /
        /
+------+-------------------------------&gt; running configuration
       ^
     Private candidate created
        </artwork>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>When is a private candidate destroyed</name>
        <t>A private candidate is valid for the duration of the NETCONF session,
        or the duration of the RESTCONF request.  Issuing
        a &lt;commit&gt; operation will not close the private candidate but will issue an
        implicit &lt;update&gt; operation resyncing changes from the running configuration.
        More details on this later in this document.</t>
        <t>A NETCONF session that is operating using a private candidate will
        discard all uncommitted changes in that session's private candidate and destroy
        the private candidate if the session is closed through a deliberate user action or
        disconnected for any other reason (such as a loss of network connectivity).</t> 
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>When is a private candidate updated</name>
        <t>An &lt;update&gt; operation performed on a private candidate triggers a 
        rebase of the private candidate configuration datastore against the running 
        configuration datastore.  This rebase is conceptually described as replacing 
        the candidate configuration datastore with the current running configuration 
        datastore at that point in time and replaying the configuration changes from 
        the candidate configuration datastore against it, identifying any conflicts 
        as this process progresses.</t>
        <t>A server may choose to automatically issue an update when any client
        updates the running configuration datastore.  Triggering an update in
        this manner must be specifically chosen and signalled by a server
        using an optional parameter to the :private-candidate NETCONF capability
        (see <xref target="how_to_signal_privcand"/>).</t>
        <t>A &lt;commit&gt; operation always issues an implicit &lt;update&gt;, 
        therefore it is not necessary for a client to perform an &lt;update&gt; 
        before a &lt;commit&gt;. The implicit &lt;update&gt; will fail if 
        conflicts are found.</t>
        <t>More details on the &lt;update&gt; operation are provided later in this
        document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="how_to_signal_privcand">
        <name>How to signal the use of private candidates</name>
        <section>
          <name>Server</name>
          <t>The server MUST signal its support for private candidates.  The server
          does this by advertising a new :private-candidate capability:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
          </sourcecode>
          <t>As support for the shared candidate configuration datastore is a 
          pre-requisite for the private candidate functionlity, a server MUST also 
          advertise the :candidate capability as defined in <xref target="RFC6241"/>.</t>
          <t>If a server chooses to execute an update operation automatically when 
          any client (not just the local client) performs an update to the running 
          configuration datastore it must advertise this behaviour using the following
          optional parameter to the capability: trigger=all-updates.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>NETCONF client</name>
          <t>In order to utilise a private candidate configuration within a NETCONF
	    session, the client must inform the server that it wishes to do this.</t>
          <t>When a NETCONF client connects with a server it sends a list of client
          capabilities including one of the :base NETCONF version capabilties.</t>
          <t>In order to enable private candidate mode for the duration of the NETCONF
          client session the NETCONF client sends the following capability:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
          </sourcecode>
          <t>In order for the use of private candidates to be established using this
          approach both the NETCONF server and the NETCONF client MUST advertise 
          this capability.</t>
          <t>If a client sends the capability and the server does not support private
          candidates, the server MUST choose one of the following options:</t>
          <ul>
          <li>Ignore the capability and continue with the session without the use of 
          private candidates (this ensures backwards compatibility with older servers).</li>
          <li>Close the session as the requested functionality cannot be provided. New 
          clients and servers implementing private candidate support should use this option.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>When a server receives the client capability its mode of operation
          will be set to private candidate mode for the duration of the NETCONF
          session.</t>
          <t>All RPC requests that target or impact the shared candidate configuration 
          datastore will implicitly target or impact the session's private candidate 
          configuration datastore instead, and operate in exactly the same way.</t>
          <t>Using this method, the use of private candidates can be made available 
          to NMDA and non-NMDA capable servers.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>RESTCONF client</name>
	  <t>RESTCONF does not provide a mechanism for the client to advertise a capability.
    Therefore when a RESTCONF server advertises the :private-candidate capability, all
         client requests will use a private candidate when the client references
         the "{+restconf}/data" resource described in
         <xref target="RFC8040" sectionFormat="of" section="3.3.1" />.
         All edits are made to the client's private candidate, and the private candidate
         is automatically committed.</t>
        <t>This ensures backwards compatibility with RESTCONF clients that are not aware of
         private candidates, because those clients will expect their changes to be
         committed immediately.</t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Interaction between running and private-candidate(s)</name>
        <t>Multiple operations may be performed on the private candidate in order
        to stage changes ready for a commit.</t>
        <t>In the simplest example, a session may create a private candidate configuration,
        perform multiple operations (such as &lt;edit-config&gt;) on it and then
        perform a &lt;commit&gt; operation to merge the private candidate configuration
        into the running configuration in line with semantics in <xref target="RFC6241"/>.
        </t>
        <artwork>
                               commit
       +--------------------------+--------&gt; private candidate
      /   ^             ^          \
     /   edit-config   edit-config  ⌄
+---+-------------------------------+------&gt; running configuration
    ^
  edit-config
  (Private candidate created)

        </artwork>
        <t>More complex scenarios need to be considered, when multiple private candidate
        sessions are working on their own configuration (branches) and they make commits
        into the running configuration.</t>
        <artwork>
                           commit
       +---------------------+----------------&gt; private candidate 1
      /                       \ 
     /         edit-config     ⌄
+---+------------+-------------+--------------&gt; running configuration
  edit-config     \
                   \
                    +-------------------------&gt; private candidate 2

        </artwork>
        <t>In this situation, if, how and when private candidate 2 is updated with the
        information that the running configuration has changed must be considered.</t>
        <t>As described earlier, the client MUST be aware of changes to its private candidate 
        configuration that are different from the running configuration datastore so it can 
        be assured that it is only committing its own modifications.</t>
        <t>It is possible, during an update, for conflicts to occur and the detection and 
        resolution of these is discussed later in this document.</t>
        <t>A good way to understand the interaction between candidates is to consider them as 
        branches such as you might find in a source code management system.</t>
        <t>Each private candidate is treated as a separate branch and changes made to the 
        running configuration are not placed into a private candidate datastore except in one 
        of the following situations:</t>
        <ul>
        <li>The client requests that the private candidate be refreshed using a new &lt;update&gt;
        operation</li>
        <li>&lt;commit&gt; is issued from the private candidate (which MUST automatically issue an 
        &lt;update&gt; operation for that private candidate immediately prior to committing the configuration)</li>
        <li>An implementation chooses to perform an &lt;update&gt; operation after a change to
        the running configuration by any other client.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>It is possible for a private candidate configuration to become significantly out of 
        sync with the running configuration should the private candidate be open for a long time,
        however, most NETCONF configuration activities (between the first 
        &lt;edit-config&gt;/&lt;edit-data&gt; and a &lt;commit&gt;) are short-lived.</t>
        <t>To provide visibility into the differences between the private candidate configuration
        datastore a <xref target="RFC9144">&lt;compare&gt;</xref> operation MAY be performed against:</t>
        <ul>
        <li>The initial creation point of the private candidate's branch</li>
        <li>Against the last update point of the private candidate's branch</li>
        <li>Against the running configuration</li>
        </ul>
        <t>An implementation may choose, optionally, to automatically perform an &lt;update&gt; 
        operation on each private candidate configuration datastore after a change to the running 
        configuration from another client.  In this situation, the client will be unaware of 
        these changes to its private candidate configuration datastore, and issuing a manual 
        &lt;update&gt; operation will be a no-op.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Detecting and resolving conflicts</name>
        <section>
          <name>What is a conflict?</name>
          <t>A conflict is when the intent of the client may have
            been different had it had a different starting point.  In configuration
            terms, a conflict occurs when the same set of nodes in a configuration being
            altered by one user are changed between the start of the configuration
            preparation (the first &lt;edit-config&gt;/&lt;edit-data&gt; operation)
            and the conclusion of this configuration activity (terminated by a
            &lt;commit&gt; operation).</t>
          <t>The situation where conflicts have the potential of occurring are when
              multiple configuration sessions are in progress and one session commits
              changes into the running configuration after the private candidate
              (branch) was created. </t>
          <t>When this happens a conflict occurs for each node modified in the running
              configuration that is also modified in the private candidate
              configuration.</t>
          <t>A node is considered modified if:</t>
          <ul>
          <li>There is a change of any value</li>
          <li>There is a change of existence (or otherwise) of any list entry</li>
          <li>There is a change to the order of any list items in a list configured as
              "ordered-by user"</li>
          <li>There is a change of existence (or otherwise) of a presence container</li>
          <li>There is a change of any component member of a leaf-list</li>
          <li>There is a change to the order of any items in a leaf-list configured as
              "ordered-by user"</li>
          <li>There is a change of existence (or otherwise) of a leaf</li>
          <li>There is a change to any YANG metadata associated with the node</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A server MAY choose to add extra checks in addition to the list above.</t>
          <t>If a server implements the transaction ID feature then this MAY be considered
          as part of detecting a conflict.</t>
          <t>Examples of conflicts include:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>An interface has been deleted in the running configuration that existed
              when the private candidate was created.  A change to a child node of this specific
                interface is made in the private candidate using the default merge operation
                would, instead of changing the child node, both recreate the interface and then
                set the child node.</li>
            <li>A leaf has been modified in the running configuration from the value that
              it had when the private candidate was created.  The private candidate configuration
              changes that leaf to another value.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Detecting and reporting conflicts</name> 
          <t>A conflict can occur when an &lt;update&gt; operation is triggered.  This
            can occur in a number of ways:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>Manually triggered by the &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation</li>
            <li>Automatically triggered by the server running an &lt;update&gt;
              operation, such as when a &lt;commit&gt; operation is performed by the 
              client in the private candidate session.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>When a conflict is identified that node is internally marked by the server as "in conflict"
          in the private candidate.  This "in conflict" status does not propagate back up 
          the tree to the parent node(s).  Each node in the ancestral tree is evaluated 
          as in conflict or otherwise on its own merits.  The "in conflict" marker 
          remains until the conflict is resolved on that node.  The mechanism by which a server
		  marks a node as "in conflict" is outside the scope of this draft.</t>
          <t>When a conflict occurs:</t>
          <ul>
          <li>The client MUST be given the opportunity to re-evaluate its intent based 
          on the new information.  The resolution of the conflict may be manual or 
          automatic depending on the server and client decision (discussed later in 
          this document).</li>
          <li>A &lt;commit&gt; operation (that MUST trigger an automatic &lt;update&gt; 
          operation immediately before) MUST fail irrespective of any system-wide 
          default resolution-mode. It MUST inform the client of the 
          conflict and SHOULD detail the location of the conflict(s).</li>
          <li>An &lt;update&gt; operation triggered by a client (excluding 
          updates triggered by the &lt;commit&gt; operation) MUST fail unless the 
          server has explicitly configured a system-wide resolution-mode of prefer-candidate 
          or prefer-running (discussed later in this document).</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The location of the conflict(s) should be reported as a list of
          xpaths and values.</t>
          <t>Note: If a server implementation has chosen to automatically issue an
          &lt;update&gt; operation every time a change is made to the running configuration,
          the server will use the system-wide system resolution mode.  If this resolution
          mode is prefer-candidate or prefer-running the conflicts will be resolved using 
          those rules. If the resolution mode is set to revert-on-conflict the semantics 
          are the same as the prefer-candidate method, however, all changes, whether in conflict or 
          otherwise will be marked in the private candidate as "in-conflict".  This means that any subsequent
          &lt;commit&gt; will fail until the client makes a conscious choice to resolve them.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="conflict_resolution">
          <name>Conflict resolution</name>
          <t>Conflict resolution defines which configuration elements are retained 
          when a conflict is resolved; those from the running configuration or 
          those from the private candidate configuration.</t>
          <t>When a conflict is detected in any client-triggered activity, the client 
          MUST be informed.  The client then has a number of options available to 
          resolve the conflict:</t>
          <ul>
          <li>Edit the candidate configuration nodes marked as "in conflict".  When a node
          marked as "in conflict" is subsequently edited the "in conflict" marker on that 
          node is removed.</li>
          <li>Issue an &lt;update&gt; operation with a specific resolution-mode.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation uses the resolution-mode specified in the 
          request, or the system resolution mode in specific circumstances, to resolve 
          the conflicts. The &lt;update&gt; operation is discussed later in this document.</t>
          <t>The following configuration data is used below to illustrate the behaviour
          of each resolution method:</t>
          <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to London&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to Tokyo&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
          </sourcecode>
          <t>The example workflow is shown in this diagram and is used for the purpose 
          of the examples below.  In these examples the reader should assume that the
          &lt;update&gt; operation is manually provided by a client working in 
          private candidate 1.  The update operation triggered by a system upon
          commit is not shown.</t>
          <artwork>
                        update commit
       +--------------------+---+------&gt; private candidate 1
      /                     ^    \
     /  edit-config        /      ⌄
+---+--------+--------+---+-------+----&gt; running configuration
 edit-config  \       ^
               \     /
                +---+------------------&gt; private candidate 2
                 commit
          </artwork>
          <t>There are three defined resolution methods:</t>
          <section>
            <name>Prefer-candidate</name>
            <t>Reminder: The starting configuration and workflow used to illustrate this
            resolution method is detailed in <xref target="conflict_resolution"/>.</t>
            <t>When using the prefer-candidate resolution method, items in the running
            configuration that are not in conflict with the private candidate
            configuration are merged from the running configuration
            into the private candidate configuration.  Nodes that are in conflict
            are ignored and not merged.  The outcome of this is that the private
            candidate configuration reflects changes in the running that were not
            being worked on and those that are being worked on in the private
            candidate remain in the private candidate.  Issuing a &lt;commit&gt;
            operation at this point will overwrite the running configuration with
            the conflicted items from the private candidate configuration.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>Session 1 edits the configuration by submitting the following</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 2 then edits the configuration deleting the
            interface intf_one, updating the description on interface
            intf_two and commits the configuration to the running
            configuration datastore.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name operation="delete"&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 1 then sends an &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="update"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;update&gt;
    &lt;resolution-mode&gt;prefer-candidate&lt;/resolution-mode&gt;
  &lt;/update&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>The un-conflicting changes are merged and the conflicting
            ones are ignored (and not merged from the running into
            private candidate 1).</t>
            <t>The resulting data in private candidate 1 is:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
            </sourcecode>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Prefer-running</name>
            <t>Reminder: The starting configuration and workflow used to illustrate this
            resolution method is detailed in <xref target="conflict_resolution"/>.</t>
            <t>When using the prefer-running resolution method, items in the running
            configuration that are not in conflict with the private candidate
            configuration are merged from the running configuration into the
            private candidate configuration.  Nodes that are in conflict are
            pushed from the running configuration into the private candidate
            configuration, overwriting any previous changes in the private
            candidate configuration.  The outcome of this is that the private
            candidate configuration reflects the changes in the running
            configuration that were not being worked on as well as changing
            those being worked on in the private candidate to new values.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>Session 1 edits the configuration by submitting the following</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 2 then edits the configuration deleting the
            interface intf_one, updating the description on interface
            intf_two and commits the configuration to the running
            configuration datastore.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name operation="delete"&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 1 then sends an &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="update"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;update&gt;
    &lt;resolution-mode&gt;prefer-running&lt;/resolution-mode&gt;
  &lt;/update&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>The un-conflicting changes are merged and the conflicting
            ones are pushed into the private candidate 1 overwriting the
            existing changes.</t>
            <t>The resulting data in private candidate 1 is:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
            </sourcecode>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Revert-on-conflict</name>
            <t>Reminder: The starting configuration and workflow used to illustrate this
            resolution method is detailed in <xref target="conflict_resolution"/>.</t>
            <t>When using the revert-on-conflict resolution method, an update
            will fail to complete when any conflicting node is found.  The
            session issuing the update will be informed of the failure.</t>
            <t>No changes, whether conflicting or un-conflicting are merged into
            the private candidate configuration.</t>
            <t>The owner of the private candidate session must then take deliberate
            and specific action to adjust the private candidate configuration to
            rectify the conflict.  This may be by issuing further &lt;edit-config&gt;
            or &lt;edit-data&gt; operations, by issuing a &lt;discard-changes&gt;
            operation or by issuing an &lt;update&gt; operation with a
            different resolution method.</t>
            <t>This resolution method MUST be the default resolution method as it
            provides for the highest level of visibility and control to ensure
            operational stability.</t>
            <t>This resolution method MUST be supported by a server.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>Session 1 edits the configuration by submitting the following:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 2 then edits the configuration deleting the
            interface intf_one, updating the description on interface
            intf_two and commits the configuration to the running
            configuration datastore.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name operation="delete"&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 1 then sends an &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="update"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;update&gt;
    &lt;resolution-mode&gt;revert-on-conflict&lt;/resolution-mode&gt;
  &lt;/update&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>A conflict is detected, the update fails with an &lt;rpc-error&gt;
            and no merges/overwrite operations happen.</t>
            <t>The resulting data in private candidate 1 is:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to Tokyo&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
            </sourcecode>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>System resolution mode and advertisement of this mode</name>
          <t>The system resolution mode is revert-on-conflict.  However, a system MAY
          choose to select a different system resolution mode.</t>
          <t>The system resolution mode only takes effect if a server implementation
          performs an automatic update to all private candidate configurations
          following a commit to running.</t>
          <t>The system resolution mode MUST be advertised in the :private-candidate
          capability by adding the default-resolution-mode parameter if the system default
          is anything other than revert-on-conflict.  If the system default resolution
          mode is revert-on-conflict then advertising this in the :private-candidate
          capability is optional.</t>
          <t>In this example, a server has configured a default system-wide resolution mode
          of prefer-running which MUST be signalled with the :private-candidate capability as 
          follows:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
              ?default-resolution-mode=prefer-running
          </sourcecode>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Supported resolution modes</name>
          <t>A server SHOULD support all three resolution modes.  However, if the server
          does not support all three modes, the server MUST report the supported modes 
          in the :private-candidate capability using the supported-resolution-modes, 
          for example:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
              ?supported-resolution-modes=revert-on-conflict,prefer-candidate
          </sourcecode>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>NETCONF operations</name>
        <section anchor="section_new_netconf_operations">
          <name>New NETCONF operations</name>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;update&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation triggers a rebase of the 
            private candidate configuration against the running configuration.  This rebase
            is conceptually described as replacing the candidate configuration with the current 
            running configuration at that point in time and replaying the configuration changes 
            from the candidate against it, identifing any conflicts as this process progresses.</t>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation may be triggered manually by the
                client or automatically by the server.</t>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation is atomic.  This means that the entire &lt;update&gt;
            operation succeeeds or the entire &lt;update&gt; operation MUST fail.</t>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation MUST be implicitly triggered by a specific 
            NETCONF session issuing a &lt;commit&gt; operation when using private
            candidates.  This implicit &lt;update&gt; operation always has a resolution
            mode of revert-on-conflict.  The actual order of operations in the server 
            MUST be to issue the implicit &lt;update&gt; operation first and then the 
            &lt;commit&gt; operation.</t>
            <t>A &lt;commit&gt; operation that fails the implicit &lt;update&gt; operation
            MUST fail.  The client is then required to make a specific decision to rectify
            the issue prior to committing.  This may be to edit the private candidate 
            configuration or to issue a manual &lt;update&gt; operation with a specific
            resolution mode selected.</t>
            <section>
              <name>&lt;resolution-mode&gt; parameter</name>
              <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation takes the optional 
                        &lt;resolution-mode&gt; parameter</t>
              <t>The resolution modes are described earlier in this document
                    and the accepted inputs are:</t>
              <ul>
                <li>revert-on-conflict (default)</li>
                <li>prefer-candidate</li>
                <li>prefer-running</li>
              </ul>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="section_updated_netconf_operations">
          <name>Updated NETCONF operations</name>
          <t>Specific NETCONF operations altered by this document are listed in this 
          section.</t>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_commit">
            <name>&lt;commit&gt;</name>
            <t>The behaviour of the &lt;commit&gt; operation is updated such that
            processing a &lt;commit&gt; MUST follow a two step process in order to 
            copy the proposed private configuration into the running configuration.  
            These steps are:</t>
            <ol>
              <li>An implicit update operation MUST be performed by the server using the
              resolution-mode revert-on-conflict (described earlier in this document).</li>
              <li>On successful completion of step 1, the private candidate configuration 
              is copied into the running configuration replacing the current contents.</li>
            </ol>
            <section anchor="section_updates_to_commit_confirmed">
              <name>Interactions with commit confirmed operations and private candidates</name>
              <t>Nothing in this document alters the behaviour of the &lt;confirmed&gt;, 
              &lt;persist&gt; or &lt;persist-id&gt; parameters and these MUST work when using the 
              a private candidate configuration if the :confirmed-commit capability is 
              advertised.</t>
              <t>When a private candidate is committed using the &lt;confirmed/&gt; parameter and
              the commit operation disconnects the client's session, the configuration in the 
              running configuration is immediately reverted and the proposed client changes 
              are discarded.</t>
              <t>When a private candidate is committed using the &lt;confirmed/&gt; parameter and
              the commit operation does not disconnect the client's session, and subsequently, the 
              commit operation is either cancelled using the &lt;cancel-commit&gt; operation or 
              the timeout expires, the running configuration is reverted and the proposed 
              client changes are returned to the client's private candidate.</t>
              <t>If a private candidate is committed using the &lt;confirmed/&gt; parameter 
              and the &lt;persist&gt; parameter is provided, and the client subsequently 
              disconnects its session for any reason whilst the timer is running, upon 
              cancellation using the &lt;cancel-commit&gt; operation or on the expiry of 
              the timer, the running configuration will be reverted, and the proposed client 
              changes are discarded.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_get_config">
            <name>&lt;get-config&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing a &lt;get-config&gt; operation with the candidate configuration datastore
            as the source input parameter will instead act on the private candidate datastore,
            and return data from that datastore. If no
            private candidate configuration has been created, one will be created at this point.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_edit_config">
            <name>&lt;edit-config&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing an &lt;edit-config&gt; operation with the candidate configuration datastore
            as the target, the changes will be placed into the private candidate configuration
            datastore.  If no private candidate configuration has been created, one will be 
            created at this point.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;copy-config&gt;</name>
            <t>When performing a &lt;copy-config&gt; operation with the candidate configuration datastore
            as the source or target, the private candidate will be used.  If no private candidate
            configuration has been created, one will be created at this point.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_get_data">
            <name>&lt;get-data&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing a &lt;get-data&gt; operation with the candidate configuration datastore
            as the datastore, the configuration from the private candidate will be returned.  If no
            private candidate configuration has been created, one will be created at this point.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_edit_data">
            <name>&lt;edit-data&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing an &lt;edit-data&gt; operation with the candidate configuration datastore
            as the datastore, the changes will be placed into the private candidate configuration
            datastore.  If no private candidate configuration has been created, one will be 
            created at this point.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_compare">
            <name>&lt;compare&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing a <xref target="RFC9144">&lt;compare&gt;</xref> operation 
                with the candidate datastore, operating as a private candidate, as 
                either the &lt;source&gt; or &lt;target&gt; is a valid operation.</t>
            <t>If &lt;compare&gt; is performed prior to a private candidate configuration
              being created, one will be created at that point.</t>
            <t>The &lt;compare&gt; operation is extended by this document to allow the ability to
            compare the private candidate (at its current point in time) with the
            same private candidate at an earlier point in time, or with another datastore.</t>
            <section>
            <name>&lt;reference-point&gt; parameter</name>
            <t>This document adds the optional &lt;reference-point&gt; node to the input of 
            the &lt;compare&gt; operation that accepts the following values:</t>
            <ul>
            <li>last-update</li>
            <li>creation-point</li>
            </ul>
            <t>Servers MAY support this functionality but are not required to by this document.</t>
            <t>The last-update selection of &lt;reference-point&gt; will provide an output
            comparing the current private candidate configuration with the same
            private candidate configuration at the time it was last updated using the &lt;update&gt; 
            NETCONF operation described in this document (whether automatically or manually triggered).</t>
            <t>The creation-point selection of &lt;reference-point&gt; will provide an output
            comparing the current private candidate configuration datastore with the same
            private candidate configuration datastore at it was first created.</t>
          </section>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;lock&gt;</name>
            <t>The behaviour of the &lt;lock&gt; operation is updated such that
            locking the candidate configuration datastore will lock that session's private
            candidate configuration datastore only.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;unlock&gt;</name>
            <t>The behaviour of the &lt;unlock&gt; operation is updated such that
            unlocking the candidate configuration datastore will unlock that session's private
            candidate configuration datastore only.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;delete-config&gt;</name>
            <t>The behaviour of the &lt;delete-config&gt; operation is updated such that
            deleting the private candidate will destroy the private candidate for that session.
            A new one will subsequently be created on first access as described in
            <xref target="section_when_created"/>.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;discard-changes&gt;</name>
            <t>The behaviour of the &lt;discard-changes&gt; operation is updated such that
            discarding the changes in a private candidate will reset it to the state it was 
            when it was initially created, or to the state following the latest &lt;update&gt;
            operation, whichever is most recent.  This state may not match the current 
            running configuration.</t>
            <t>To align the private candidate with the running configuration the &lt;update&gt;
            or &lt;delete-config&gt; operations may be used.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;get&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;get&gt; operation does not accept a datastore value and therefore
              this document is not applicable to this operation.  The use of the
              get operation will not create a private candidate configuration.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
                <name>&lt;cancel-commit&gt;</name>
                <t>The &lt;cancel-commit&gt; operation is unchanged.  Any changes made to the running
                configuration are returned to the private candidate if it still exists. See 
                <xref target="section_updates_to_commit_confirmed"/> for further details.</t>
          </section>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document requests the registration the the following NETCONF capabilities:</t>
      <ul><li>urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0 (Version 1.0)</li></ul>
      <t>This document also requests the registration of the following YANG modules in the
      YANG Module Names registry and in the IETF XML:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>ietf-netconf-private-candidate</li>
        <li>ietf-netconf-private-candidate-compare</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The "ietf-netconf-private-candidate" and "ietf-netconf-private-candidate-compare" YANG modules 
      define data models that are designed to be accessed via YANG-based management protocols, such as 
      NETCONF [RFC6241] and RESTCONF [RFC8040]. These YANG-based management protocols (1) have to use 
      a secure transport layer (e.g., SSH [RFC4252], TLS [RFC8446], and QUIC [RFC9000]) and (2) have 
      to use mutual authentication.</t>
      <t>The Network Configuration Access Control Model (NACM) [RFC8341] provides the means to restrict 
      access for particular NETCONF or RESTCONF users to a preconfigured subset of all available NETCONF 
      or RESTCONF protocol operations and content.</t>
      <t>Some of the RPC or action operations in this YANG module may be considered sensitive or 
      vulnerable in some network environments. It is thus important to control access to these 
      operations. Specifically, the following operations have particular sensitivities/vulnerabilities:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>&lt;update&gt;:  This operation modifies the private candidate configuration based on the 
        current running configuration. Unauthorized access to this operation could lead to 
        unintended configuration changes in the private candidate.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9144.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5717.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8526.xml"/>
        <!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section>
      <name>YANG modules</name>
      <section>
        <name>ietf-netconf-private-candidate@2026-02-03.yang</name>
        <sourcecode type="yang" markers="true" name="ietf-netconf-private-candidate@2026-02-03.yang">
<![CDATA[
module ietf-netconf-private-candidate {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-netconf-private-candidate";
  prefix pc;

  
  organization
    "IETF NETCONF (Network Configuration) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <http://tools.ietf.org/wg/netconf/>
     WG List:  <netconf@ietf.org>

     Editor:   James Cumming
            <james.cumming@nokia.com>

     Editor:   Robert Wills
            <rowills@cisco.com>";
  description
    "NETCONF private candidate support.

     Copyright (c) <year> IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject to
     the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License set
     forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX
     (https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfcXXXX); see the RFC itself
     for full legal notices.

     The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL', 'SHALL
     NOT', 'SHOULD', 'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'NOT RECOMMENDED',
     'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this document are to be interpreted as
     described in BCP 14 (RFC 2119) (RFC 8174) when, and only when,
     they appear in all capitals, as shown here.";

  revision 2026-02-03 {
    description
      "Introduce private candidate support";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand:
       Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2025-10-30 {
    description
      "Introduce private candidate support";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand:
       Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2024-09-12 {
    description
      "Introduce private candidate support";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand:
       Netconf Private Candidates";
  }

  feature private-candidate {
    description
      "NETCONF :private-candidate capability;
       If the server advertises the :private-candidate
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
  }

  rpc update {
    if-feature "private-candidate";
    description
      "Updates the private candidate from the running
       configuration.";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
    input {
      leaf resolution-mode {
        type enumeration {
          enum revert-on-conflict {
            description
              "Reject update when any conflicting
               node is found and revert the private
               candidate configuration datastore to its
               state prior to issuing the update.";
          }
          enum prefer-candidate {
            description
              "Resolve conflicted node by selecting
               the private candidate configuration
               datastore version.";
          }
          enum prefer-running {
            description
              "Resolve conflicted node by selecting
               the running configuration datastore
               version.";
          }
        }
        default "revert-on-conflict";
        description
          "Mode to resolve conflicts between running and
           private-candidate configurations.";
      }
    }
  }
}
]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>ietf-netconf-private-candidate-compare@2026-02-03.yang</name>
        <sourcecode type="yang" markers="true" name="ietf-netconf-private-candidate-compare@2026-02-03.yang">
<![CDATA[
module ietf-netconf-private-candidate-compare {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-netconf-private-candidate-compare";
  prefix pccmp;

  import ietf-netconf-private-candidate {
    prefix pc;
  }
  import ietf-nmda-compare {
    prefix cmp;
  }

  organization
    "IETF NETCONF (Network Configuration) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <http://tools.ietf.org/wg/netconf/>
     WG List:  <netconf@ietf.org>

     Editor:   James Cumming
            <james.cumming@nokia.com>

     Editor:   Robert Wills
            <rowills@cisco.com>";
  description
    "NETCONF private candidate support.

     Copyright (c) <year> IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject to
     the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License set
     forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX
     (https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfcXXXX); see the RFC itself
     for full legal notices.

     The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL', 'SHALL
     NOT', 'SHOULD', 'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'NOT RECOMMENDED',
     'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this document are to be interpreted as
     described in BCP 14 (RFC 2119) (RFC 8174) when, and only when,
     they appear in all capitals, as shown here.";

  revision 2026-02-03 {
    description
      "Introduce private candidate support";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand:
       Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2025-10-30 {
    description
      "Introduce private candidate support";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand:
       Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2024-09-12 {
    description
      "Introduce private candidate support";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand:
       Netconf Private Candidates";
  }

  augment "/cmp:compare/cmp:input" {
    if-feature "pc:private-candidate";
    description
      "Augment private candidate extensions into the NETCONF compare
       RPC";
    leaf reference-point {
      type enumeration {
        enum last-update {
          description
            "Compare using the point the private
             candidate configuration datastore was
             last updated using the update or commit
             RPCs.";
        }
        enum creation-point {
          description
            "Compare using the point the private
             candidate configuration datastore was
             initially created.";
        }
      }
      default "last-update";
      description
        "When this leaf is provided and the source or
         destination is the candidate datastore, operating
         in private candidate mode, the comparison will
         either occur between the last-update point of
         the private candidate or the creation-point of
         the private candidate.";
      reference
        "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
    }
  }
}
]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank Andy Bierman, Jan Lindblad, Lori-Ann McGrath, 
      Dylan Sadoun, Jason Sterne, Kent Watsen and Rob Wilton for their reviews and 
      feedback.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
