<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- 
     draft-rfcxml-general-template-standard-01
  
     This template includes examples of the most commonly used features of RFCXML with comments 
     explaining how to customise them. This template can be quickly turned into an I-D by editing 
     the examples provided. Look for [REPLACE], [REPLACE/DELETE], [CHECK] and edit accordingly.
     Note - 'DELETE' means delete the element or attribute, not just the contents.
     
     Documentation is at https://authors.ietf.org/en/templates-and-schemas
-->
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
      category="std" 
      docName="draft-ietf-netconf-privcand-04" 
      ipr="trust200902" 
      obsoletes="" 
      updates="6241,8342,8526,9144" 
      submissionType="IETF" 
      xml:lang="en" 
      version="3"
      consensus="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="NETCONF Private Candidates">NETCONF Private Candidates</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-netconf-privcand-04"/>
    <author fullname="James Cumming" initials="JG" surname="Cumming">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <email>james.cumming@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Robert Wills" initials="R" surname="Wills">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rowills@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024" month="07" day="02"/>
    <!-- On draft subbmission:
         * If only the current year is specified, the current day and month will be used.
         * If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, the current day will
           be used
         * If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month and day="1" will be used.
    -->
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- "Internet Engineering Task Force" is fine for individual submissions.  If this element is 
          not present, the default is "Network Working Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as 
          a nod to the history of the RFC Series. -->
    <keyword>NETCONF</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a mechanism to extend the Network Configuration Protocol 
	     (NETCONF) and RESTCONF protocol to support multiple clients making configuration changes simultaneously and
         ensuring that they commit only those changes that they defined.</t>
      <t>This document addresses two specific aspects: The interaction with a private candidate
        over the NETCONF and RESTCONF protocols and the methods to identify and resolve conflicts between
        clients.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC6241">NETCONF</xref> and <xref target="RFC8040">RESTCONF</xref>
	       both provide a mechanism for one or more
         clients to make configuration changes to a device running as a NETCONF/RESTCONF
         server.  Each client has the ability to make one or more
         configuration changes to the server's shared candidate configuration.<br/><br/>
		 
		 As the name shared candidate suggests, all clients have access to the same candidate
		 configuration.  This means that multiple clients may make changes to the shared
		 candidate prior to the configuration being committed.  This behaviour may be
		 undesirable as one client may unwittingly commit the configuration changes made
		 by another client.  <br/><br/>
		 
		 NETCONF provides a way to mitigate this behaviour by allowing clients
		 to place a lock on the shared candidate.  The placing of this lock means that
		 no other client may make any changes until that lock is released.  This behaviour
		 is, in many situations, also undesirable.  <br/><br/>

		 Many network devices already support private candidate configurations,
		 where a user (machine or otherwise) is able to edit a personal copy of a device's
		 configuration without blocking other users from doing so.<br/><br/>
	 
	     This document details the extensions to the NETCONF protocol in order to support
	     the use of private candidates.  It also describes how the RESTCONF protocol can be
	     used on a system that implements private candidates.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Updates to RFC 6241 and RFC 8526</name>
        <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC6241"/> to augment the
          NETCONF &lt;edit-config&gt;, &lt;copy-config&gt;, &lt;get-config&gt;,
          &lt;commit&gt;, &lt;lock&gt; and &lt;unlock&gt; operations to
          describe how they work with a private candidate datastore.  These
          updates are described in
          <xref target="section_updated_netconf_operations"/>.  This
	  document also adds a new &lt;update&gt; operation, described in
	  <xref target="section_new_netconf_operations"/>.</t>
        <t>This document also updates <xref target="RFC8526"/> to augment the
          NETCONF &lt;edit-data&gt; and &lt;get-data&gt; operations to
          describe how they work with a private candidate datastore.  These
          updates are described in
          <xref target="section_updated_netconf_operations"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Updates to RFC 8342</name>
        <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC8342"/> to show how the
          private candidate datastore relates to other datastores.  This is
          shown in <xref target="section_private_candidate_datastore"/>.</t>
	<t>Specifially, NMDA is updated to add additional writeable
	  configuration datastores called private candidates.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Updates to RFC 9144</name>
        <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC9144"/> to augment the
          &lt;compare&gt; operation to describe how it works with the
          private candidate datastore.  These updates are described in
          <xref target="section_updates_to_compare"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Definitions and terminology</name>
      <section>
        <name>Session specific datastore</name>
        <t>A session specific datastore is a configuration datastore that,
          unlike the candidate and running configuration datastores which
          have only one per system, is bound to the specific NETCONF session.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Shared candidate configuration</name>
        <t>The candidate configuration datastore defined in
          <xref target="RFC6241"/> is referenced as the shared candidate
          configuration in this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Private candidate configuration</name>
        <t>A private candidate configuration is a session specific candidate
          configuration datastore.</t>
        <t>When a private candidate is used by NETCONF, the specific session
	  (and user) that created the private
          candidate configuration is the only session (user) that has access
          to it over NETCONF.  Devices may expose this to other users through
          other interfaces but this is out of scope for this document.</t>
	    <t>When a private candidate is used by RESTCONF, the client that created
          the private candidate configuration is the only client that has access
          to it over RESTCONF.</t>
        <t>The private candidate configuration contains a full copy of the running
          configuration when it is created (in the same way as a branch does in
          a source control management system and in the same way as the candidate
          configuration datastore as defined in <xref target="RFC6241"/>).
          Any changes made to it, for example, through the use of operations such
          as &lt;edit-config&gt; and &lt;edit-data&gt;, are made in this private
          candidate configuration.</t>
        <t>Obtaining this private candidate over NETCONF or RESTCONF will display the entire
          configuration, including all changes made to it.  Performing a &lt;commit&gt;
          operation will merge the changes from the private candidate into the
          running configuration (the same as a merge in source code management systems).
          A &lt;discard-changes&gt; operation will revert the private candidate to the
          branch's initial state or it's state at the last &lt;commit&gt; (whichever
          is most recent).</t>
        <t>All changes made to this private candidate configuration are held
           separately from any other candidate configuration changes, whether
           made by other users to the shared candidate or any other private candidate,
           and are not visible to or accessible by anyone else.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Limitations using the shared candidate configuration for multiple clients</name>
      <t>The following sections describe some limitations and mitigation factors in
      more detail for the use of the shared candidate configuration during multi-client
      configuration over NETCONF or RESTCONF.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Issues</name>
        <section>
          <name>Unintended deployment of alternate users configuration changes</name>
          <t>Consider the following scenario:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>Client 1 modifies item A in the shared candidate configuration</li>
            <li>Client 2 then modifies item B in the shared candidate configuration</li>
            <li>Client 2 then issues a &lt;commit&gt; RPC</li>
          </ol>
          <t>In this situation, both client 1 and client 2 configurations will be committed by
            client 2.  In a machine-to-machine environment client 2 may not have been aware of
            the change to item A and, if they had been aware, may have decided not to proceed.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Current mitigation strategies</name>
        <section>
          <name>Locking the shared candidate configuration datastore</name>
          <t>
            In order to resolve unintended deployment of alternate users configuration changes
            as described above NETCONF provides the ability to lock a datastore in order to
            restrict other users from editing and committed changes.
          </t>
          <t>This does resolve the specific issue above, however, it introduces another issue.
             Whilst one of the clients holds a lock, no other client may edit the configuration.
             This will result in the client failing and having to retry.  Whilst this may be a
             desirable consequence when two clients are editing the same section of the configuration,
             where they are editing different sections this behaviour may hold up valid operational
             activity.</t>
          <t>Additionally, a lock placed on the shared candidate configuration must also lock the
          running configuration, otherwise changes committed directly into the running datastore
          may conflict.</t>
	  <t>Finally, this locking mechanism isn't available to RESTCONF clients.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Always use the running configuration datastore</name>
          <t>The use of the running configuration datastore as the target for all configuration
          changes does not resolve any issues regarding blocking of system access in the case a
          lock is taken, nor does it provide a solution for multiple NETCONF and RESTCONF clients as each
          configuration change is applied immediately and the client has no knowledge of the
          current configuration at the point in time that they commenced the editing activity nor
          at the point they commit the activity.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Fine-grained locking</name>
          <t><xref target="RFC5717"/> describes a partial lock mechanism that
            can be used on specific portions of the shared candidate datastore.</t>
          <t>Partial locking does not solve the issues of staging a set of
             configuration changes such that only those changes get committed in a
             commit operation, nor does it solve the issue of multiple clients
             editing the same parts of the configuration at the same time.</t>
          <t>Partial locking additionally requires that the client is aware of
          any interdependencies within the servers YANG models in order to lock all
          parts of the tree.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Private candidates solution</name>
      <t>The use of private candidates resolves the issues
        detailed earlier in this document.</t>
      <t>NETCONF sessions and RESTCONF clients are able to utilize private candidates
         to streamline network operations, particularly for
         machine-to-machine communication.</t>
      <t>Using this approach, clients may improve their performance and reduce the
        likelihood of blocking other clients from continuing with valid operational
        activities.</t>
      <t>One or more private candidates may exist at any one time, however, a
        private candidate SHOULD:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>Be accessible by one client only</li>
        <li>Be visible by one client only</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Additionally, the choice of using a shared candidate configuration
         datastore or a private candidate configuration datastore MUST be for
         the entire duration of the NETCONF session.</t>
      <section>
        <name>What is a private candidate</name>
        <t>A private candidate is defined earlier in the definitions and terminology
          section of this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="section_when_created">
        <name>When is a private candidate created</name>
        <t>A private candidate datastore is created when the first RPC that requires access
        to it is sent to the server.  This could be, for example, an &lt;edit-config&gt;.</t>
        <t>When the private candidate is created a copy of the running configuration is
        made and stored in it.  This can be considered the same as creating a branch in a
        source code repository.</t>
        <artwork>
          +----------------------------&gt; private candidate
         /
        /
+------+-------------------------------&gt; running configuration
       ^
     Private candidate created
        </artwork>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>When is a private candidate destroyed</name>
        <t>A private candidate is valid for the duration of the NETCONF session,
        or the duration of the existence of the RESTCONF client.  Issuing
        a &lt;commit&gt; operation will not close the private candidate but will issue an
        implicit &lt;update&gt; operation resyncing changes from the running configuration.
        More details on this later in this document.</t>
        <t>A NETCONF session that is operating using a private candidate will
        discard all uncommitted changes in that session's private candidate and destroy
        the private candidate if the session is closed through a deliberate user action or
        disconnected for any other reason (such as a loss of network connectivity).</t> 
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>How to signal the use of private candidates</name>
        <section>
          <name>Server</name>
          <t>The server MUST signal its support for private candidates.  The server
          does this by advertising a new :private-candidate capability:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
          </sourcecode>
          <t>A server may also advertise the :candidate capability as defined in
          <xref target="RFC6241"/> if the shared candidate is also supported.</t>
          <t>A non-NMDA capable NETCONF server that advertises the :private-candidate
          capability MUST also advertise the :candidate capability.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>NETCONF client</name>
          <t>In order to utilise a private candidate configuration within a NETCONF
	    session, the client must inform the server that it wishes to do this.</t>
          <t>Two approaches are available for a NETCONF client to signal that it wants
            to use a private candidate:</t>
          <section>
            <name>Client capability declaration</name>
            <t>When a NETCONF client connects with a server it sends a list of client
            capabilities including one of the :base NETCONF version capabilties.</t>
            <t>In order to enable private candidate mode for the duration of the NETCONF
            client session the NETCONF client sends the following capability:</t>
            <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
            </sourcecode>
            <t>In order for the use of private candidates to be established using this
            approach both the NETCONF server and the NETCONF client MUST advertise 
            this capability.</t>
            <t>When a server receives the client capability its mode of operation
             will be set to private candidate mode for the duration of the NETCONF
             session.</t>
            <t>All RPC requests that target the candidate configuration datastore
            will operate in exactly the same way as they would do when using the
            shared candidate configuration datastore, however, when the server
            receives a request to act upon the candidate configuration datastore it
            instead uses the session's private candidate configuration datastore.</t>
            <t>Using this method, the use of private candidates can be made available 
            to NMDA and non-NMDA capable servers.</t>
            <t>No protocol extensions are required for the transitioning of candidates between
            the shared mode and the private mode and no extensions are required for any
            RPCs (including &lt;lock&gt;)</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_private_candidate_datastore">
            <name>Private candidate datastore</name>
            <t>The private candidate configuration datastore is exposed as its
             own datastore similar to other <xref target="RFC8342">NMDA</xref>
             capable datastores.  This datastore is called private-candidate.</t>
<artwork><![CDATA[

+-------------+                 +-----------+       +---------------------+
| <candidate> |                 | <startup> |       | <private-candidate> |-+
|  (ct, rw)   |<---+       +--->| (ct, rw)  |    +->|     (ct, rw)        | |-+
+-------------+    |       |    +-----------+    |  +---------------------+ | |
      |           |       |           |         |    +----------------------+ | 
      |         +-----------+<--------+         |      +----------------------+  
      +-------->| <running> |                   |            |  // multiple
                | (ct, rw)  |-------------------+            |  // private-candidates
                +-----------+<-------------------------------+  // possible
                      |
                      |        // configuration transformations,
                      |        // e.g., removal of nodes marked as
                      |        // "inactive", expansion of
                      |        // templates
                      v
                +------------+
                | <intended> | // subject to validation
                | (ct, ro)   |
                +------------+
                      |        // changes applied, subject to
                      |        // local factors, e.g., missing
                      |        // resources, delays
                      |
  dynamic              |   +-------- learned configuration
  configuration        |   +-------- system configuration
  datastores -----+    |   +-------- default configuration
                  |    |   |
                  v    v   v
              +---------------+
              | <operational> | <-- system state
              | (ct + cf, ro) |
              +---------------+

ct = config true; cf = config false
rw = read-write; ro = read-only
boxes denote named datastores
]]>
</artwork>

            <t>All NMDA operations that support candidate NMDA datastore SHOULD
            support the private-candidate datastore.</t>
            <t>Any non-NMDA aware NETCONF operations that take a source or target
             (destination) may be extended to accept the new datastore.</t>
            <t>The ability for the server to support private candidates is optional
            and SHOULD be signalled in NMDA supporting servers as a datastore in addition
            to the server capabilities described earlier in this document.</t>
            <t>To use this method the client is not required to send the
            :private-candidate capability.</t>
            <t>The first datastore referenced (either candidate or private-candidate) in
             any NETCONF operation will define which mode that NETCONF session will
             operate in for its duration.  As an example, performing a &lt;get-data&gt;
             operation on the private-candidate datastore will switch the session into
             private candidate configuration mode and subsequent &lt;edit-config&gt;
             operations that reference the candidate configuration datastore MUST fail.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>RESTCONF client</name>
	  <t>RESTCONF doesn't provide a mechanism for the client to advertise a capability.
    Therefore when a RESTCONF server advertises the :private-candidate capability, the
    decision of whether to use a private candidate depends on whether a datastore is
    explicitly referenced in the request using the RESTCONF extensions for NMDA
	  <xref target="RFC8527"/>.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Datastore is not explicitly referenced</name>
	    <t>When the server advertises the :private-candidate capability and the client
         references the "{+restconf}/data" resource described in
         <xref target="RFC8040" sectionFormat="of" section="3.3.1" />,
         all edits are made to the client's private candidate, and the private candidate
         is automatically committed.</t>
        <t>This ensures backwards compatibility with RESTCONF clients that are not aware of
         private candidates, because those clients will expect their changes to be
         committed immediately.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Private candidate datastore is referenced in the request</name>
	    <t>When the private-candidate datastore is explicitly referenced as an NMDA datastore,
         edits are made to the client's private candidate, but the private candidate is not
         committed.  To commit the changes, the client must explicitly send a commit request.</t>
        <t>A commit request is of the form "{+restconf}/operations/ietf-netconf:commit",
         using the API described in <xref target="RFC8040" sectionFormat="of" section="3.3.2" />.
         The semantics are identical to the NETCONF &lt;commit&gt; operation.</t>
        <t>Similarly, the client can perform ietf-netconf:discard-changes,
         ietf-netconf:validate, and ietf-netconf:cancel-commit operations (if the appropriate
         capabilities are implemented).  The semantics are identical to NETCONF.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Identifying the private candidate datastore</name>
        <t>Each RESTCONF client has its own private candidate datastore.  The client
         (and hence the private candidate datastore) is identified using the mechanism
         described in <xref target="RFC8040" sectionFormat="of" section="2.5" />.</t>
      </section>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Interaction between running and private-candidate(s)</name>
        <t>Multiple operations may be performed on the private candidate in order
        to stage changes ready for a commit.</t>
        <t>In the simplest example, a session may create a private candidate configuration,
        perform multiple operations (such as &lt;edit-config&gt;) on it and then
        perform a &lt;commit&gt; operation to merge the private candidate configuration
        into the running configuration in line with semantics in <xref target="RFC6241"/>.
        </t>
        <artwork>
                               commit
       +--------------------------+--------&gt; private candidate
      /   ^             ^          \
     /   edit-config   edit-config  ⌄
+---+-------------------------------+------&gt; running configuration
    ^
  edit-config
  (Private candidate created)

        </artwork>
        <t>More complex scenarios need to be considered, when multiple private candidate
        sessions are working on their own configuration (branches) and they make commits
        into the running configuration.</t>
        <artwork>
                           commit
       +---------------------+----------------&gt; private candidate 1
      /                       \ 
     /         edit-config     ⌄
+---+------------+-------------+--------------&gt; running configuration
  edit-config     \
                   \
                    +-------------------------&gt; private candidate 2

        </artwork>
        <t>In this situation, if, how and when private candidate 2 is updated with the
        information that the running configuration has changed must be considered.</t>
        <t>As described earlier, the client MUST be aware of changes to it's private candidate 
        configuration so it can be assured that it is only committing its own modifications. 
        It should also be aware of any changes to the current running configuration.</t>
        <t>It is possible, during an update, for conflicts to occur and the detection and 
        resolution of these is discussed later in this document.</t>
        <t>A good way to understand the interaction between candidates is to consider them as 
        branches such as you might find in a source code management system.</t>
        <t>Each private candidate is treated as a separate branch and changes made to the 
        running configuration are not placed into a private candidate datastore except in one 
        of the following situations:</t>
        <ul>
        <li>The client requests that the private candidate be refreshed using a new &lt;update&gt;
        operation</li>
        <li>&lt;commit&gt; is issued (which MUST automatically issue an &lt;update&gt; operation 
        immediately prior to committing the configuration)</li>
        <li>An implmentation chooses to perform an &lt;update&gt; operation after a change to
        the running configuration by any other client</li>
        </ul>
        <t>It is possible for a private candidate configuration to become significantly out of 
        sync with the running configuration should the private candidate be open for a long time,
        however, most NETCONF configuration activities (between the first 
        &lt;edit-config&gt;/&lt;edit-data&gt; and a &lt;commit&gt;) are short-lived.</t>
        <t>An implementation may choose, optionally, to automatically perform an &lt;update&gt; 
        operation after a change to the running configuration from another client.  However, this
        choice should be made with caution as it will replace, overwrite, or otherwise alter 
        (depending on the servers default resolution mode, discussed later) the private candidate
        configuration without notifying the client.</t>
        <t>A &lt;compare&gt; operation MAY be performed against:</t>
        <ul>
        <li>The initial creation point of the private candidate's branch</li>
        <li>Against the last update point of the private candidate's branch</li>
        <li>Against the running configuration</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Detecting and resolving conflicts</name>
        <section>
          <name>What is a conflict?</name>
          <t>A conflict is when the intent of the client may have
            been different had it had a different starting point.  In configuration
            terms, a conflict occurs when the same set of nodes in a configuration being
            altered by one user are changed between the start of the configuration
            preparation (the first &lt;edit-config&gt;/&lt;edit-data&gt; operation)
            and the conclusion of this configuration activity (terminated by a
            &lt;commit&gt; operation).</t>
          <t>The situation where conflicts have the potential of occurring are when
              multiple configuration sessions are in progress and one session commits
              changes into the running configuration after the private candidate
              (branch) was created. </t>
          <t>When this happens a conflict occurs for each node modified in the running
              configuration that is also modified in the private candidate
              configuration.</t>
          <t>A node is considered modified if:</t>
          <ul>
          <li>There is a change of any value</li>
          <li>There is a change of existence (or otherwise) of any list entry</li>
          <li>There is a change to the order of any list items in a list configured as
              "ordered-by user"</li>
          <li>There is a change of existence (or otherwise) of a presence container</li>
          <li>There is a change of any component member of a leaf-list</li>
          <li>There is a change to the order of any items in a leaf-list configured as
              "ordered-by user"</li>
          <li>There is a change of existance (or otherwise) of a leaf with an Empty type
          definition</li>
          <li>There is a change to any YANG metadata associated with the node</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A server MAY choose to add additional checks over and above the above
          list.</t>
          <t>If a server implements the transaction ID feature then this MAY be considered
          as part of detecting a conflict.</t>
          <t>When a conflict is identified that node is marked by the server as "in conflict"
          in the private candidate.  This "in conflict" status does not propagate back up 
          the tree to the parent node(s).  Each node in the ancestral tree is evaluated 
          as in conflict or otherwise on its own merits.  The "in conflict" marker 
          remains until the conflict is resolved on that node.</t>
          <t>Examples of conflicts include:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>An interface has been deleted in the running configuration that existed
              when the private candidate was created.  A change to a child node of this specific
                interface is made in the private candidate using the default merge operation
                would, instead of changing the child node, both recreate the interface and then
                set the child node.</li>
            <li>A leaf has been modified in the running configuration from the value that
              it had when the private candidate was created.  The private candidate configuration
              changes that leaf to another value.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Detecting and reporting conflicts</name>
          <t>A conflict can occur when an &lt;update&gt; operation is triggered.  This
            can occur in a number of ways:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>Manually triggered by the &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation</li>
            <li>Automatically triggered by the server running an &lt;update&gt;
              operation, such as when a &lt;commit&gt; operation is performed by the 
              client in the private candidate session.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>When a conflict occurs:</t>
          <ul>
          <li>The client MUST be given the opportunity to re-evaluate its intent based 
          on the new information.  The resolution of the conflict may be manual or 
          automatic depending on the server and client decision (discussed later in 
          this document).</li>
          <li>A &lt;commit&gt; operation (that MUST trigger an automatic &lt;update&gt; 
          operation immediately before) MUST fail. It MUST inform the client of the 
          conflict and SHOULD detail the location of the conflict(s).</li>
          <li>A &lt;update&gt; operation MUST fail unless the server has explicitly 
          configured a system-wide default resolution mode of ignore or overwrite
          (discussed later in this document)</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The location of the conflict(s) should be reported as a list of
          xpaths and values.</t>
          <t>Note: If a server implementation has chosen to automatically issue an
          &lt;update&gt; operation every time a change is made to the running configuration,
          the server will use the system-wide default resolution mode.  If this resolution
          mode is ignore or overwrite the conflicts will be resolved using those rules. If
          the resolution mode is set to revert-on-conflict the semantics are the same as
          the ignore method, however, all changes, whether in conflict or otherwise will
          be marked in the private candidate as "in-conflict".  This means that any subsequent
          &lt;commit&gt; will fail until the client makes a conscious choice to resolve them.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Conflict resolution</name>
          <t>Conflict resolution defines which configuration elements are retained 
          when a conflict is resolved; those from the running configuration or 
          those from the private candidate configuration.</t>
          <t>When a conflict is detected in any client-triggered activity, the client 
          MUST be informed.  The client then has a number of options available to 
          resolve the conflict.</t>
          <t>An &lt;update&gt; operation uses the resolution method specified in the
          request, or the system default resolution mode if not specified.  The &lt;update&gt;
          operation is discussed later in this document.</t>
          <t>The following configuration data is used below to illustrate the behaviour
          of each resolution method:</t>
          <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to London&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to Tokyo&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
          </sourcecode>
          <t>The example workflow is shown in this diagram and is used for the purpose 
          of the examples below.  In these examples the reader should assume that the
          &lt;update&gt; operation is manually provided by a client working in 
          private candidate 1.</t>
          <artwork>
                        update commit
       +--------------------+---+------&gt; private candidate 1
      /                     ^    \
     /  edit-config        /      ⌄
+---+--------+--------+---+-------+----&gt; running configuration
 edit-config  \       ^
               \     /
                +---+------------------&gt; private candidate 2
                 commit
          </artwork>
          <t>There are three defined resolution methods:</t>
          <section>
            <name>Ignore</name>
            <t>Reminder: The starting configuration and workflow used to illustrate this
            resolution method is detailed in the parent chapter of this document.</t>
            <t>When using the ignore resolution method, items in the running
            configuration that are not in conflict with the private candidate
            configuration are merged from the running configuration
            into the private candidate configuration.  Nodes that are in conflict
            are ignored and not merged.  The outcome of this is that the private
            candidate configuration reflects changes in the running that were not
            being worked on and those that are being worked on in the private
            candidate remain in the private candidate.  Issuing a &lt;commit&gt;
            operation at this point will overwrite the running configuration with
            the conflicted items from the private candidate configuration.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>Session 1 edits the configuration by submitting the following</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 2 then edits the configuration deleting the
            interface intf_one, updating the description on interface
            intf_two and commits the configuration to the running
            configuration datastore.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name operation="delete"&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 1 then sends an &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="update"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;update&gt;
    &lt;resolution-mode&gt;ignore&lt;/resolution-mode&gt;
  &lt;/update&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>The un-conflicting changes are merged and the conflicting
            ones are ignored (and not merged from the running into
            private candidate 1).</t>
            <t>The resulting data in private candidate 1 is:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
            </sourcecode>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Overwrite</name>
            <t>Reminder: The starting configuration and workflow used to illustrate this
            resolution method is detailed in the parent chapter of this document.</t>
            <t>When using the overwrite resolution method, items in the running
            configuration that are not in conflict with the private candidate
            configuration are merged from the running configuration into the
            private candidate configuration.  Nodes that are in conflict are
            pushed from the running configuration into the private candidate
            configuration, overwriting any previous changes in the private
            candidate configuration.  The outcome of this is that the private
            candidate configuration reflects the changes in the running
            configuration that were not being worked on as well as changing
            those being worked on in the private candidate to new values.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>Session 1 edits the configuration by submitting the following</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 2 then edits the configuration deleting the
            interface intf_one, updating the description on interface
            intf_two and commits the configuration to the running
            configuration datastore.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name operation="delete"&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 1 then sends an &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="update"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;update&gt;
    &lt;resolution-mode&gt;overwrite&lt;/resolution-mode&gt;
  &lt;/update&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>The un-conflicting changes are merged and the conflicting
            ones are pushed into the private candidate 1 overwriting the
            existing changes.</t>
            <t>The resulting data in private candidate 1 is:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
            </sourcecode>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Revert-on-conflict</name>
            <t>Reminder: The starting configuration and workflow used to illustrate this
            resolution method is detailed in the parent chapter of this document.</t>
            <t>When using the revert-on-conflict resolution method, an update
            will fail to complete when any conflicting node is found.  The
            session issuing the update will be informed of the failure.</t>
            <t>No changes, whether conflicting or un-conflicting are merged into
            the private candidate configuration.</t>
            <t>The owner of the private candidate session must then take deliberate
            and specific action to adjust the private candidate configuration to
            rectify the conflict.  This may be by issuing further &lt;edit-config&gt;
            or &lt;edit-data&gt; operations, by issuing a &lt;discard-changes&gt;
            operation or by issuing an &lt;update&gt; operation with a
            different resolution method.</t>
            <t>This resolution method is the default resolution method as it
            provides for the highest level of visibility and control to ensure
            operational stability.</t>
            <t>This resolution method MUST be supported by a server.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>Session 1 edits the configuration by submitting the following:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 2 then edits the configuration deleting the
            interface intf_one, updating the description on interface
            intf_two and commits the configuration to the running
            configuration datastore.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="config"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;edit-config&gt;
    &lt;target&gt;&lt;candidate/&gt;&lt;target&gt;
    &lt;config&gt;
      &lt;configure&gt;
        &lt;interfaces&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name operation="delete"&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
          &lt;interface&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;Link moved to Paris&lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;/interface&gt;
        &lt;/interfaces&gt;
      &lt;/configure&gt;
    &lt;/config&gt;
  &lt;/edit-config&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>Session 1 then sends an &lt;update&gt; NETCONF operation.</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;rpc message-id="update"
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"&gt;
  &lt;update&gt;
    &lt;resolution-mode&gt;revert-on-conflict&lt;/resolution-mode&gt;
  &lt;/update&gt;
&lt;/rpc&gt;
            </sourcecode>
            <t>A conflict is detected, the update fails with an &lt;rpc-error&gt;
            and no merges/overwrite operations happen.</t>
            <t>The resulting data in private candidate 1 is:</t>
            <sourcecode type="xml">
&lt;configure&gt;
  &lt;interfaces&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_one&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to San Francisco&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    &lt;interface&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;intf_two&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Link to Tokyo&lt;description&gt;
    &lt;/interface&gt;
  &lt;/interfaces&gt;
&lt;/configure&gt;
            </sourcecode>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Default resolution mode and advertisement of this mode</name>
          <t>The default resolution mode is revert-on-conflict.  However, a system MAY
          choose to select a different default resolution mode.</t>
          <t>The default resolution mode MUST be advertised in the :private-candidate
          capability by adding the default-resolution-mode parameter if the system default
          is anything other than revert-on-conflict.  If the system default resolution
          mode is revert-on-conflict then advertising this in the :private-candidate
          capability is optional.</t>
          <t>In this example, a server has configured a default system-wide resolution mode
          of overwrite which MUST be signalled with the :private-candidate capability as 
          follows:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
              ?default-resolution-mode=overwrite
          </sourcecode>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Supported resolution modes</name>
          <t>A server SHOULD support all three resolution modes.  However, if the server
          does not support all three modes, the server MUST report the supported modes 
          in the :private-candidate capability using the supported-resolution-modes, 
          for example:</t>
          <sourcecode>
urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0
              ?supported-resolution-modes=revert-on-conflict,ignore
          </sourcecode>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>NETCONF operations</name>
        <section anchor="section_new_netconf_operations">
          <name>New NETCONF operations</name>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;update&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation is provided to allow NETCONF clients
                (or servers) to trigger a rebase of the private candidate configuration
                    against the running configuration.</t>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation may be triggered manually by the
                client or automatically by the server.</t>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation is atomic.  This means that the entire &lt;update&gt;
            operation succeeeds or the entire &lt;update&gt; operation MUST fail.</t>
            <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation MUST be implicitly triggered by a specific 
            NETCONF session issuing a &lt;commit&gt; operation when using private
            candidates.  The actual order of operations in the server MUST be to issue 
            the implicit &lt;update&gt; operation first and then the &lt;commit&gt; 
            operation.</t>
            <t>A &lt;commit&gt; operation that fails the implicit &lt;update&gt; operation
            SHOULD fail.  The client is then required to make a specific decision to rectify
            the issue prior to committing.  This may be to edit the private candidate 
            configuration or to issue a manual &lt;update&gt; operation with a specific
            resolution mode selected.</t>
            <section>
              <name>&lt;resolution-mode&gt; parameter</name>
              <t>The &lt;update&gt; operation takes the optional 
                        &lt;resolution-mode&gt; parameter</t>
              <t>The resolution modes are described earlier in this document
                    and the accepted inputs are:</t>
              <ul>
                <li>revert-on-conflict (default)</li>
                <li>ignore</li>
                <li>overwrite</li>
              </ul>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="section_updated_netconf_operations">
          <name>Updated NETCONF operations</name>
          <t>Specific NETCONF operations altered by this document are listed in this section.
            Any notable behaviour with existing unaltered NETCONF operations is noted in the
            appendix.</t>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;edit-config&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;edit-config&gt; operation is updated to accept
                    private-candidate as valid input to the &lt;target&gt; field.</t>
            <t>The use of &lt;edit-config&gt; will create a private candidate
                  configuration if one does not already exist for that NETCONF
                  session.</t>
            <t>Sending an &lt;edit-config&gt; request to private-candidate
                  after one has been sent to the shared candidate datastore
                  in the same session will fail (and visa-versa).</t>
            <t>Multiple &lt;edit-config&gt; requests may be sent to the
                  private-candidate datastore in a single session.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;edit-data&gt;</name>
            <t>The <xref target="RFC8526">&lt;edit-data&gt;</xref> operation is updated to accept
                    private-candidate as valid input to the &lt;datastore&gt; field.
                    (datastore is an identityref and so the actual input will be 
                    ds:private-candidate).</t>
            <t>The use of &lt;edit-data&gt; will create a private candidate
                  configuration if one does not already exist for that NETCONF
                  session.</t>
            <t>Multiple &lt;edit-data&gt; requests may be sent to the
                  private-candidate datastore in a single session.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;lock&gt; and &lt;unlock&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing a &lt;lock&gt; on the private-candidate datastore is a valid operation, although
            the practical effect of this is a 'no op' as only one session may edit
            the locked private candidate.</t>
            <t>If the client's intention is that no other session may commit changes to the system then
            the client should issue a &lt;lock&gt; operation on the running datastore.</t>
            <t>Other NETCONF sessions are still able to create a new private-candidate
                configurations, make edits to them and perform operations on them, such as 
                &lt;update&gt; or &lt;discard-changes&gt;.</t>
            <t>Performing an &lt;unlock&gt; on the private-candidate datastore is a valid operation.</t>
            <t>Changes in the private-candidate datastore are not lost when the lock is released.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="section_updates_to_compare">
            <name>&lt;compare&gt;</name>
            <t>Performing a <xref target="RFC9144">&lt;compare&gt;</xref> operation 
                with the private-candidate datastore as either the &lt;source&gt;
                or &lt;target&gt; is a valid operation.</t>
            <t>If &lt;compare&gt; is performed prior to a private candidate configuration
              being created, one will be created at that point.</t>
            <t>The &lt;compare&gt; operation is extended by this document to allow the ability to
            compare the private-candidate datastore (at its current point in time) with the
            same private-candidate datastore at an earlier point in time or with another datastore.</t>
            <section>
            <name>&lt;reference-point&gt; parameter</name>
            <t>This document adds the optional &lt;reference-point&gt; node to the input of 
            the &lt;compare&gt; operation that accepts the following values:</t>
            <ul>
            <li>last-update</li>
            <li>creation-point</li>
            </ul>
            <t>Servers MAY support this functionality but are not required to by this document.</t>
            <t>The last-update selection of &lt;reference-point&gt; will provide an output
            comparing the current private-candidate configuration datastore with the same
            private-candidate datastore at the time it was last updated using the &lt;update&gt; 
            NETCONF operation described in this document (whether automatically or manually triggered).</t>
            <t>The creation-point selection of &lt;reference-point&gt; will provide an output
            comparing the current private-candidate configuration datastore with the same
            private-candidate datastore at the time this private-candidate was initially created.</t>
          </section>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;get-config&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;get-config&gt; operation is updated to accept private-candidate as
              valid input to the &lt;source&gt; field.</t>
            <t>The use of &lt;get-config&gt; will create a private candidate configuration
              if one does not already exist for that NETCONF session.</t>
            <t>Sending an &lt;get-config&gt; request to private-candidate
                  after one has been sent to the shared candidate datastore
                  in the same session will fail (and visa-versa).</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;get-data&gt;</name>
            <t>The <xref target="RFC8526">&lt;get-data&gt;</xref> operation accepts
              the private-candidate as a valid datastore.</t>
            <t>The use of &lt;get-data&gt; will create a private candidate configuration
              if one does not already exist for that NETCONF session.</t>
            <t>Sending an &lt;get-data&gt; request to private-candidate
                  after one has been sent to the shared candidate datastore
                  in the same session will fail (and visa-versa).</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;copy-config&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;copy-config&gt; operation is updated to accept private-candidate as
          a valid input to the &lt;source&gt; or &lt;target&gt; fields.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;validate&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;validate&gt; operation is updated to accept private-candidate as
              valid input to the &lt;source&gt; field.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;delete-config&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;delete-config&gt; operation is updated to accept private-candidate as
          a valid input to the &lt;target&gt; field.</t>
          <t>Deleting the private candidate will destroy the private candidate for the client.
          A new one will subsequently be created on first access as described in
          <xref target="section_when_created" />.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;discard-changes&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;discard-changes&gt; operation is updated to accept private-candidate
            as a valid input to the newly added &lt;target&gt; field.</t>
            <t>Discarding the change to the private candidate will reset it to the state it
            was when it was initially created, or to the state following the latest &lt;update&gt;
            operation, whichever is most recent.  This state may not match the current 
            running configuration.</t>
            <t>To align the private candidate with the running configuration the &lt;update&gt;
            or &lt;delete-config&gt; operations may be used.</t>
            <t>If the &lt;target&gt; field is not provided with the &lt;private-candidate/&gt;
            parameter then the behaviour from <xref target="RFC6241"/> remains and the shared candidate changes
            are discarded.</t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>&lt;commit&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;commit&gt; operation MUST trigger an implicit &lt;update&gt; operation
            immediately before copying the private candidate configuration into the running
            configuration.</t>
            <section>
              <name>Interactions with commit confirmed operations and private candidates</name>
              <t>Nothing in this document alters the behaviour of the &lt;confirmed&gt;, 
              &lt;persist&gt; or &lt;persist-id&gt; parameters and these MUST work when using the 
              private-candidate configuration datastore if the :confirmed-commit capability is 
              advertised.</t>
              <t>When a private candidate is committed using the &lt;confirmed/&gt; parameter and
              the commit operation disconnects the client's session, the configuration in the 
              running configuration is immediately reverted and the proposed client changes 
              are discarded.</t>
              <t>When a private candidate is committed using the &lt;confirmed/&gt; parameter and
              the commit operation does not disconnect the client's session, and subsequently, the 
              commit operation is either cancelled using the &lt;cancel-commit&gt; operation or 
              the timeout expires, the running configuration is reverted and the proposed 
              client changes are returned to the client's private candidate.</t>
              <t>If a private candidate is committed using the &lt;confirmed/&gt; parameter 
              and the &lt;persist&gt; parameter is provided, and the client subsequently 
              disconnects its session for any reason whilst the timer is running, upon 
              cancellation using the &lt;cancel-commit&gt; operation or on the expiry of 
              the timer, the running configuration will be reverted, and the proposed client 
              changes are discarded.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document requests the registration the the following NETCONF capabilities:</t>
      <ul><li>urn:ietf:params:netconf:capability:private-candidate:1.0 (Version 1.0)</li></ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8342.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9144.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5717.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8526.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8527.xml"/>
        <!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section>
      <name>Behaviour with unaltered NETCONF operations</name>
      <section>
        <name>&lt;get&gt;</name>
        <t>The &lt;get&gt; operation does not accept a datastore value and therefore
          this document is not applicable to this operation.  The use of the
          get operation will not create a private candidate configuration.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
            <name>&lt;cancel-commit&gt;</name>
            <t>The &lt;cancel-commit&gt; operation is unchanged.  Any changes made to the running
            configuration are returned to the private candidate if it still exists.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <name>YANG modules</name>
      <section>
        <name>ietf-netconf@2024-04-16.yang</name>
        <sourcecode type="yang" markers="true" name="ietf-netconf@2024-04-16.yang">
<![CDATA[
module ietf-netconf {

  // the namespace for NETCONF XML definitions is unchanged
  // from RFC 4741, which this document replaces

  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0";
  prefix nc;

  import ietf-inet-types {
    prefix inet;
  }

  organization
    "IETF NETCONF (Network Configuration) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <http://tools.ietf.org/wg/netconf/>
     WG List:  <netconf@ietf.org>

     WG Chair: Bert Wijnen
               <bertietf@bwijnen.net>

     WG Chair: Mehmet Ersue
               <mehmet.ersue@nsn.com>

     Editor:   Martin Bjorklund
               <mbj@tail-f.com>

     Editor:   Juergen Schoenwaelder
               <j.schoenwaelder@jacobs-university.de>

     Editor:   Andy Bierman
               <andy.bierman@brocade.com>

     Editor:   James Cumming
               <james.cumming@nokia.com>

     Editor:   Robert Wills
               <rowills@cisco.com>";
  description
    "NETCONF Protocol Data Types and Protocol Operations.

     Copyright (c) 2024 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code. All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust’s Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC 6241 and
     draft-ietf-netconf-privcand; see these documents for full
     legal notices.";

  revision 2024-04-16 {
    description
      "Updated to introduce private candidates";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand: Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2011-06-01 {
    description
      "Initial revision";
    reference
      "RFC 6241: Network Configuration Protocol";
  }

  extension get-filter-element-attributes {
    description
      "If this extension is present within an 'anyxml'
       statement named 'filter', which must be conceptually
       defined within the RPC input section for the <get>
       and <get-config> protocol operations, then the
       following unqualified XML attribute is supported
       within the <filter> element, within a <get> or
       <get-config> protocol operation:

         type : optional attribute with allowed
                value strings 'subtree' and 'xpath'.
                If missing, the default value is 'subtree'.

       If the 'xpath' feature is supported, then the
       following unqualified XML attribute is
       also supported:

         select: optional attribute containing a
                 string representing an XPath expression.
                 The 'type' attribute must be equal to 'xpath'
                 if this attribute is present.";
  }

  // NETCONF capabilities defined as features

  feature writable-running {
    description
      "NETCONF :writable-running capability;
       If the server advertises the :writable-running
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.2";
  }

  feature candidate {
    description
      "NETCONF :candidate capability;
       If the server advertises the :candidate
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.3";
  }

  feature private-candidate {
    description
      "NETCONF :private-candidate capability;
       If the server advertises the :private-candidate
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
  }

  feature confirmed-commit {
    if-feature "candidate";
    description
      "NETCONF :confirmed-commit:1.1 capability;
       If the server advertises the :confirmed-commit:1.1
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.4";
  }

  feature rollback-on-error {
    description
      "NETCONF :rollback-on-error capability;
       If the server advertises the :rollback-on-error
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.5";
  }

  feature validate {
    description
      "NETCONF :validate:1.1 capability;
       If the server advertises the :validate:1.1
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.6";
  }

  feature startup {
    description
      "NETCONF :startup capability;
       If the server advertises the :startup
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.7";
  }

  feature url {
    description
      "NETCONF :url capability;
       If the server advertises the :url
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.8";
  }

  feature xpath {
    description
      "NETCONF :xpath capability;
       If the server advertises the :xpath
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.9";
  }

  // NETCONF Simple Types

  typedef session-id-type {
    type uint32 {
      range "1..max";
    }
    description
      "NETCONF Session Id";
  }

  typedef session-id-or-zero-type {
    type uint32;
    description
      "NETCONF Session Id or Zero to indicate none";
  }

  typedef error-tag-type {
    type enumeration {
      enum in-use {
        description
          "The request requires a resource that
           already is in use.";
      }
      enum invalid-value {
        description
          "The request specifies an unacceptable value for one
           or more parameters.";
      }
      enum too-big {
        description
          "The request or response (that would be generated) is
           too large for the implementation to handle.";
      }
      enum missing-attribute {
        description
          "An expected attribute is missing.";
      }
      enum bad-attribute {
        description
          "An attribute value is not correct; e.g., wrong type,
           out of range, pattern mismatch.";
      }
      enum unknown-attribute {
        description
          "An unexpected attribute is present.";
      }
      enum missing-element {
        description
          "An expected element is missing.";
      }
      enum bad-element {
        description
          "An element value is not correct; e.g., wrong type,
           out of range, pattern mismatch.";
      }
      enum unknown-element {
        description
          "An unexpected element is present.";
      }
      enum unknown-namespace {
        description
          "An unexpected namespace is present.";
      }
      enum access-denied {
        description
          "Access to the requested protocol operation or
           data model is denied because authorization failed.";
      }
      enum lock-denied {
        description
          "Access to the requested lock is denied because the
           lock is currently held by another entity.";
      }
      enum resource-denied {
        description
          "Request could not be completed because of
           insufficient resources.";
      }
      enum rollback-failed {
        description
          "Request to roll back some configuration change (via
           rollback-on-error or <discard-changes> operations)
           was not completed for some reason.";
      }
      enum data-exists {
        description
          "Request could not be completed because the relevant
           data model content already exists.  For example,
           a 'create' operation was attempted on data that
           already exists.";
      }
      enum data-missing {
        description
          "Request could not be completed because the relevant
           data model content does not exist.  For example,
           a 'delete' operation was attempted on
           data that does not exist.";
      }
      enum operation-not-supported {
        description
          "Request could not be completed because the requested
           operation is not supported by this implementation.";
      }
      enum operation-failed {
        description
          "Request could not be completed because the requested
           operation failed for some reason not covered by
           any other error condition.";
      }
      enum partial-operation {
        description
          "This error-tag is obsolete, and SHOULD NOT be sent
           by servers conforming to this document.";
      }
      enum malformed-message {
        description
          "A message could not be handled because it failed to
           be parsed correctly.  For example, the message is not
           well-formed XML or it uses an invalid character set.";
      }
    }
    description
      "NETCONF Error Tag";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Appendix A";
  }

  typedef error-severity-type {
    type enumeration {
      enum error {
        description
          "Error severity";
      }
      enum warning {
        description
          "Warning severity";
      }
    }
    description
      "NETCONF Error Severity";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 4.3";
  }

  typedef edit-operation-type {
    type enumeration {
      enum merge {
        description
          "The configuration data identified by the
           element containing this attribute is merged
           with the configuration at the corresponding
           level in the configuration datastore identified
           by the target parameter.";
      }
      enum replace {
        description
          "The configuration data identified by the element
           containing this attribute replaces any related
           configuration in the configuration datastore
           identified by the target parameter.  If no such
           configuration data exists in the configuration
           datastore, it is created.  Unlike a
           <copy-config> operation, which replaces the
           entire target configuration, only the configuration
           actually present in the config parameter is affected.";
      }
      enum create {
        description
          "The configuration data identified by the element
           containing this attribute is added to the
           configuration if and only if the configuration
           data does not already exist in the configuration
           datastore.  If the configuration data exists, an
           <rpc-error> element is returned with an
           <error-tag> value of 'data-exists'.";
      }
      enum delete {
        description
          "The configuration data identified by the element
           containing this attribute is deleted from the
           configuration if and only if the configuration
           data currently exists in the configuration
           datastore.  If the configuration data does not
           exist, an <rpc-error> element is returned with
           an <error-tag> value of 'data-missing'.";
      }
      enum remove {
        description
          "The configuration data identified by the element
           containing this attribute is deleted from the
           configuration if the configuration
           data currently exists in the configuration
           datastore.  If the configuration data does not
           exist, the 'remove' operation is silently ignored
           by the server.";
      }
    }
    default "merge";
    description
      "NETCONF 'operation' attribute values";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.2";
  }

  // NETCONF Standard Protocol Operations

  rpc get-config {
    description
      "Retrieve all or part of a specified configuration.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.1";
    input {
      container source {
        description
          "Particular configuration to retrieve.";
        choice config-source {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration to retrieve.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               source.";
          }
          leaf running {
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config source.
               This is optional-to-implement on the server because
               not all servers will support filtering for this
               datastore.";
          }
        }
      }
      anyxml filter {
        description
          "Subtree or XPath filter to use.";
        nc:get-filter-element-attributes;
      }
    }
    output {
      anyxml data {
        description
          "Copy of the source datastore subset that matched
           the filter criteria (if any).  An empty data container
           indicates that the request did not produce any results.";
      }
    }
  }

  rpc edit-config {
    description
      "The <edit-config> operation loads all or part of a specified
       configuration to the specified target configuration.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.2";
    input {
      container target {
        description
          "Particular configuration to edit.";
        choice config-target {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration target.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               target.";
          }
          leaf running {
            if-feature "writable-running";
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config source.";
          }
        }
      }
      leaf default-operation {
        type enumeration {
          enum merge {
            description
              "The default operation is merge.";
          }
          enum replace {
            description
              "The default operation is replace.";
          }
          enum none {
            description
              "There is no default operation.";
          }
        }
        default "merge";
        description
          "The default operation to use.";
      }
      leaf test-option {
        if-feature "validate";
        type enumeration {
          enum test-then-set {
            description
              "The server will test and then set if no errors.";
          }
          enum set {
            description
              "The server will set without a test first.";
          }
          enum test-only {
            description
              "The server will only test and not set, even
               if there are no errors.";
          }
        }
        default "test-then-set";
        description
          "The test option to use.";
      }
      leaf error-option {
        type enumeration {
          enum stop-on-error {
            description
              "The server will stop on errors.";
          }
          enum continue-on-error {
            description
              "The server may continue on errors.";
          }
          enum rollback-on-error {
            description
              "The server will roll back on errors.
               This value can only be used if the 'rollback-on-error'
               feature is supported.";
          }
        }
        default "stop-on-error";
        description
          "The error option to use.";
      }
      choice edit-content {
        mandatory true;
        description
          "The content for the edit operation.";
        anyxml config {
          description
            "Inline Config content.";
        }
        leaf url {
          if-feature "url";
          type inet:uri;
          description
            "URL-based config content.";
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc copy-config {
    description
      "Create or replace an entire configuration datastore with the
       contents of another complete configuration datastore.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.3";
    input {
      container target {
        description
          "Particular configuration to copy to.";
        choice config-target {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration target of the copy operation.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               target.";
          }
          leaf running {
            if-feature "writable-running";
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config target.
               This is optional-to-implement on the server.";
          }
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf url {
            if-feature "url";
            type inet:uri;
            description
              "The URL-based configuration is the config target.";
          }
        }
      }
      container source {
        description
          "Particular configuration to copy from.";
        choice config-source {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration source for the copy operation.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               source.";
          }
          leaf running {
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf url {
            if-feature "url";
            type inet:uri;
            description
              "The URL-based configuration is the config source.";
          }
          anyxml config {
            description
              "Inline Config content: <config> element.  Represents
               an entire configuration datastore, not
               a subset of the running datastore.";
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc delete-config {
    description
      "Delete a configuration datastore.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.4";
    input {
      container target {
        description
          "Particular configuration to delete.";
        choice config-target {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration target to delete.";
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               target.";
          }
          leaf url {
            if-feature "url";
            type inet:uri;
            description
              "The URL-based configuration is the config target.";
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc lock {
    description
      "The lock operation allows the client to lock the configuration
       system of a device.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.5";
    input {
      container target {
        description
          "Particular configuration to lock.";
        choice config-target {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration target to lock.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               target.";
          }
          leaf running {
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config target.";
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc unlock {
    description
      "The unlock operation is used to release a configuration lock,
       previously obtained with the 'lock' operation.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.6";
    input {
      container target {
        description
          "Particular configuration to unlock.";
        choice config-target {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration target to unlock.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               target.";
          }
          leaf running {
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config target.";
          }
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config target.";
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc get {
    description
      "Retrieve running configuration and device state information.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.7";
    input {
      anyxml filter {
        description
          "This parameter specifies the portion of the system
           configuration and state data to retrieve.";
        nc:get-filter-element-attributes;
      }
    }
    output {
      anyxml data {
        description
          "Copy of the running datastore subset and/or state
           data that matched the filter criteria (if any).
           An empty data container indicates that the request did not
           produce any results.";
      }
    }
  }

  rpc close-session {
    description
      "Request graceful termination of a NETCONF session.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.8";
  }

  rpc kill-session {
    description
      "Force the termination of a NETCONF session.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 7.9";
    input {
      leaf session-id {
        type session-id-type;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Particular session to kill.";
      }
    }
  }

  rpc commit {
    if-feature "candidate";
    if-feature "private-candidate";
    description
      "Commit the candidate or private candidate configuration
       as the device's new current configuration.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.3.4.1 and draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
    input {
      leaf confirmed {
        if-feature "confirmed-commit";
        type empty;
        description
          "Requests a confirmed commit.";
        reference
          "RFC 6241, Section 8.3.4.1";
      }
      leaf confirm-timeout {
        if-feature "confirmed-commit";
        type uint32 {
          range "1..max";
        }
        units "seconds";
        default "600"; // 10 minutes
        description
          "The timeout interval for a confirmed commit.";
        reference
          "RFC 6241, Section 8.3.4.1";
      }
      leaf persist {
        if-feature "confirmed-commit";
        type string;
        description
          "This parameter is used to make a confirmed commit
           persistent.  A persistent confirmed commit is not aborted
           if the NETCONF session terminates.  The only way to abort
           a persistent confirmed commit is to let the timer expire,
           or to use the <cancel-commit> operation.

           The value of this parameter is a token that must be given
           in the 'persist-id' parameter of <commit> or
           <cancel-commit> operations in order to confirm or cancel
           the persistent confirmed commit.

           The token should be a random string.";
        reference
          "RFC 6241, Section 8.3.4.1";
      }
      leaf persist-id {
        if-feature "confirmed-commit";
        type string;
        description
          "This parameter is given in order to commit a persistent
           confirmed commit.  The value must be equal to the value
           given in the 'persist' parameter to the <commit>
           operation. If it does not match, the operation fails
           with an 'invalid-value' error.";
        reference
          "RFC 6241, Section 8.3.4.1";
      }
    }
  }

  rpc discard-changes {
    if-feature "candidate";
    if-feature "private-candidate";
    description
      "Revert the candidate configuration to the current
       running configuration.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.3.4.2";
    input {
      container target {
        if-feature "private-candidate";
        reference "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
        description
          "Particular configuration to discard changes from.";
        choice config-target {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration target to discard.";
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               target.";
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc cancel-commit {
    if-feature "confirmed-commit";
    description
      "This operation is used to cancel an ongoing confirmed commit.
       If the confirmed commit is persistent, the parameter
       'persist-id' must be given, and it must match the value of the
       'persist' parameter.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.4.4.1";
    input {
      leaf persist-id {
        type string;
        description
          "This parameter is given in order to cancel a persistent
           confirmed commit.  The value must be equal to the value
           given in the 'persist' parameter to the <commit>
           operation.  If it does not match, the operation fails
           with an 'invalid-value' error.";
      }
    }
  }

  rpc update {
    if-feature "private-candidate";
    description
      "Updates the private candidate from the running
       configuration.";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
    input {
      leaf resolution-mode {
        description
          "Mode to resolve conflicts between running and
           private-candidate configurations.";
        default revert-on-conflict;
        type enumeration {
          enum revert-on-conflict;
          enum ignore;
          enum overwrite;
        }
      }
    }
  }

  rpc validate {
    if-feature "validate";
    description
      "Validates the contents of the specified configuration.";
    reference
      "RFC 6241, Section 8.6.4.1";
    input {
      container source {
        description
          "Particular configuration to validate.";
        choice config-source {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The configuration source to validate.";
          leaf candidate {
            if-feature "candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The candidate configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf private-candidate {
            if-feature "private-candidate";
            type empty;
            description
              "The private candidate configuration is the config
               source.";
          }
          leaf running {
            type empty;
            description
              "The running configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf startup {
            if-feature "startup";
            type empty;
            description
              "The startup configuration is the config source.";
          }
          leaf url {
            if-feature "url";
            type inet:uri;
            description
              "The URL-based configuration is the config source.";
          }
          anyxml config {
            description
              "Inline Config content: <config> element.  Represents
               an entire configuration datastore, not
               a subset of the running datastore.";
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }
}
]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>ietf-datastores@2024-04-16.yang</name>
        <sourcecode type="yang" markers="true" name="ietf-datastores@2024-04-16.yang">
<![CDATA[
module ietf-datastores {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-datastores";
  prefix ds;

  organization
    "IETF Network Modeling (NETMOD) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/netmod/>

     WG List:  <mailto:netmod@ietf.org>

     Author:   Martin Bjorklund
               <mailto:mbj@tail-f.com>

     Author:   Juergen Schoenwaelder
               <mailto:j.schoenwaelder@jacobs-university.de>

     Author:   Phil Shafer
               <mailto:phil@juniper.net>

     Author:   Kent Watsen
               <mailto:kwatsen@juniper.net>

     Author:   Rob Wilton
               <rwilton@cisco.com>

     Author:   James Cumming
               <james.cumming@nokia.com>

     Author:   Robert Wills
               <rowills@cisco.com>";
  description
    "This YANG module defines a set of identities for identifying
     datastores.

     Copyright (c) 2024 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code. All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust’s Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC 8342
     (https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8342); and
     draft-ietf-netconf-privcand.  See these documents
     for full legal notices.";

  revision 2024-04-16 {
    description
      "Updated to introduce private candidates";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand: Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2018-02-14 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC 8342: Network Management Datastore Architecture (NMDA)";
  }

  /*
   * Identities
   */

  identity datastore {
    description
      "Abstract base identity for datastore identities.";
  }

  identity conventional {
    base datastore;
    description
      "Abstract base identity for conventional configuration
       datastores.";
  }

  identity running {
    base conventional;
    description
      "The running configuration datastore.";
  }

  identity candidate {
    base conventional;
    description
      "The candidate configuration datastore.";
  }

  identity private-candidate {
    base conventional;
    description
      "The private candidate configuration datastore.";
  }

  identity startup {
    base conventional;
    description
      "The startup configuration datastore.";
  }

  identity intended {
    base conventional;
    description
      "The intended configuration datastore.";
  }

  identity dynamic {
    base datastore;
    description
      "Abstract base identity for dynamic configuration datastores.";
  }

  identity operational {
    base datastore;
    description
      "The operational state datastore.";
  }

  /*
   * Type definitions
   */

  typedef datastore-ref {
    type identityref {
      base datastore;
    }
    description
      "A datastore identity reference.";
  }
}

]]>



        </sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>ietf-nmda-compare@2024-04-16.yang</name>
        <sourcecode type="yang" markers="true" name="ietf-nmda-compare@2024-04-16.yang">
<![CDATA[
module ietf-nmda-compare {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-nmda-compare";
  prefix cmp;

  import ietf-yang-types {
    prefix yang;
    reference
      "RFC 6991: Common YANG Data Types";
  }
  import ietf-datastores {
    prefix ds;
    reference
      "RFC 8342: Network Management Datastore
       Architecture (NMDA)";
  }
  import ietf-yang-patch {
    prefix ypatch;
    reference
      "RFC 8072: YANG Patch Media Type";
  }
  import ietf-netconf {
    prefix nc;
    reference
      "RFC 6241: Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF)";
  }

  organization
    "IETF NETMOD (Network Modeling) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/netmod/>
     WG List:  <mailto:netmod@ietf.org>

     Author: Alexander Clemm
             <mailto:ludwig@clemm.org>

     Author: Yingzhen Qu
             <mailto:yqu@futurewei.com>

     Author: Jeff Tantsura
             <mailto:jefftant.ietf@gmail.com>

     Author: Andy Bierman
             <mailto:andy@yumaworks.com>
             
     Author: James Cumming
             <mailto:james.cumming@nokia.com>
        
     Author: Robert Wills
             <mailto:rowills@cisco.com>";
  description
    "The YANG data model defines a new operation, <compare>, that
     can be used to compare NMDA datastores.

     Copyright (c) 2021 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject to
     the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License set
     forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC 9144; see the
     RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2024-04-16 {
    description
      "Updated to introduce private candidates";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand: Netconf Private Candidates";
  }
  revision 2021-12-10 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC 9144: Comparison of Network Management Datastore
       Architecture (NMDA) Datastores";
  }

  feature private-candidate {
    description
      "NETCONF :private-candidate capability;
       If the server advertises the :private-candidate
       capability for a session, then this feature must
       also be enabled for that session.  Otherwise,
       this feature must not be enabled.";
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
  }

  /* RPC */

  rpc compare {
    description
      "NMDA datastore compare operation.";
    input {
      leaf source {
        type identityref {
          base ds:datastore;
        }
        mandatory true;
        description
          "The source datastore to be compared.";
      }
      leaf target {
        type identityref {
          base ds:datastore;
        }
        mandatory true;
        description
          "The target datastore to be compared.";
      }
      leaf reference-point {
        reference "draft-ietf-netconf-privcand";
        if-feature "private-candidate";
        description 
          "When this leaf is provided and the source or
           destination are the private-candidate datastore,
           the comparison will either occur between the
           last-update point of the private candidate or the
           creation-point of the private candidate.";
        default last-update;
        type enumeration {
          enum last-update;
          enum creation-point;
        }
      }
      leaf all {
        type empty;
        description
          "When this leaf is provided, all data nodes are compared,
           whether their schema node pertains to both datastores or
           not.  When this leaf is omitted, a prefiltering step is
           automatically applied that excludes data nodes from the
           comparison that can occur in only one datastore but not
           the other.  Specifically, if one of the datastores
           (source or target) contains only configuration data and
           the other datastore is <operational>, data nodes for
           the config that is false are excluded from the
           comparison.";
      }
      leaf report-origin {
        type empty;
        description
          "When this leaf is provided, origin metadata is
           included as part of RPC output.  When this leaf is
           omitted, origin metadata in comparisons that involve
           <operational> is by default omitted.";
      }
      choice filter-spec {
        description
          "Identifies the portions of the datastores to be
               compared.";
        anydata subtree-filter {
          description
            "This parameter identifies the portions of the
             target datastore to retrieve.";
          reference
            "RFC 6241, Section 6.";
        }
        leaf xpath-filter {
          if-feature "nc:xpath";
          type yang:xpath1.0;
          description
            "This parameter contains an XPath expression
             identifying the portions of the target
             datastore to retrieve.";
          reference
            "RFC 6991: Common YANG Data Types";
        }
      }
    }
    output {
      choice compare-response {
        description
          "Comparison results.";
        leaf no-matches {
          type empty;
          description
            "This leaf indicates that the filter did not match
             anything and nothing was compared.";
        }
        container differences {
          description
            "The list of differences, encoded per RFC 8072 with an
             augmentation to include source values where applicable.
             When a datastore node in the source is not present in
             the target, this can be indicated either as a 'delete'
             or as a 'remove' as there is no difference between
             them for the purposes of the comparison.";
          uses ypatch:yang-patch {
            augment "yang-patch/edit" {
              description
                "Provides the value of the source of the patch,
                 respectively of the source of the comparison, in
                 addition to the target value, where applicable.";
              anydata source-value {
                when "../operation = 'delete'"
                   + "or ../operation = 'merge'"
                   + "or ../operation = 'move'"
                   + "or ../operation = 'replace'"
                   + "or ../operation = 'remove'";
                description
                  "The anydata 'value' is only used for 'delete',
                   'move', 'merge', 'replace', and 'remove'
                   operations.";
              }
              reference
                "RFC 8072: YANG Patch Media Type";
            }
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }
}

]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank Andy Bierman, Jan Lindblad, Lori-Ann McGrath, Jason Sterne, 
      Kent Watsen and Rob Wilton for their contributions and reviews.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
